<!-- Module User's Guide -->

<chapter>
	<title>&adminguide;</title>

	<section id="overview" xreflabel="Overview">
		<title>Overview</title>
		<para>
		TLS, as defined in SIP RFC 3261, is a mandatory feature for proxies
		and can be used to secure the SIP signalling on a hop-by-hop basis
		(not end-to-end). TLS works on top of TCP. DTLS, or TLS over UDP is
		already defined by IETF and may become available in the future.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>History</title>
		<para>
		The TLS support was originally developed by Peter Griffiths and posted
		as a patch on SER development mailing list. Thanks to Cesc
		Santasusana, several problems were fixed and some improvements were
		added.
		</para>
		<para>
		The TLS support was simultaneously added in both projects. In SER,
		the support was committed in a separate <quote>experimental</quote>
		CVS tree, as patch to the main CVS tree. In OpenSIPS, the support was
		integrated directly into the CVS tree, as a built-in component, and is
		part of stable OpenSIPS since release >=1.0.0.
		</para>
		<para>
		Starting with OpenSIPS 2.1, the TLS has been moved to a separate
		transport module, that implements the more generic Transport
		Interface.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Scenario</title>
		<para>
		By the increased number of providers the SIP world is continuously
		growing. More users means more calls and more calls means a high
		probability for a user to receive calls from totally unknown people
		or, in the worst case, to receive unwanted calls. To prevent this, a
		defense mechanism must be adopted by the SIP provider. Since only the
		called user is fully able to classify a call as being unwanted, the
		SIP server, based on all information regarding the call should notify
		the user about the desirability of the call. Information like the
		caller domain, the received source or the incoming protocol can be
		very useful for a SIP server to establish the nature of the call.
		</para>
		<para>
		As this information is quite limited, is very improbable for a server
		to be able detect the unwanted calls - there are many calls that it
		cannot predict anything about its status (neutral calls). So, instead
		on alerting the called user about unwanted calls, the server can
		notify the user about calls that are considered trusted - calls for
		which the server is 100% sure there are not unwanted.
		</para>
		<para>
		So, a trust concept must be defined for SIP servers. Which calls
		are trusted and which are not? A call is trusted if the caller can
		be identify as a trustable user - a user about we have reliable
		information.
		</para>
		<para>
		Since all the user from its domain are authenticated (or should be),
		a SIP server can consider all the calls generated by its user as
		trusted. Now we have to extend the trust concept to the multi-domain
		level. A mutual agreement, between several domains, can establish a
		trusting relationship. So, a domain (called A) will consider also as
		trusted calls all the calls generated by user from a different domain
		(called B) and vice-versa. But just an agreement is not enough; since
		the authentication information is strictly limited to a domain
		(a domain can authenticate only its own user, not the user from other
		domains), there is still the problem of checking the authenticity of
		the caller - he can impersonate (by a false FROM header) a user from
		a domain that is trusted.
		</para>
		<para>
		The answer to this problem is TLS (Transport Layer Security). All
		calls via domain A and domain B will be done via TLS. Authentication
		in origin domain plus TLS transport between domains will make the
		call 100% trusted for the target domain.
		</para>
		<para>
		For such a mechanism to work, the following requirements must be met:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			all UA must have set as outbound proxy their home server.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			all SIP servers must authenticated all the calls generated by
			their own users.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para>all SIP servers must relay the calls generated be their
			user to a trusted domain via TLS.
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
		Based on this, a server can classify as trusted a call for one of
		its user only if the call is also generated by one of its users or
		is the call is received from a trusted domain ( which is equivalent
		with a call received via TLS). Untrusted call will be calls received
		from users belonging to untrusted domains or from users from trusted
		domains, but whose calls are not routed via their home server
		(so, they are not authenticated by there home servers).
		</para>
		<para>
		Once the server is able to tell if the call is trusted or not, the
		still open issue is about the mechanism used by server to notify the
		called user about the nature of the incoming call.
		</para>
		<para>
		One way to do it is by remotely changing the ringing type of the
		called user's phone. This can be done by inserting special header
		into the INVITE request. Such feature is supported by now by several
		hardphones like CISCO ATA, CISCO 7960 and SNOM. This phones can
		change their ringing tone based on the present or content of the
		"Alert-Info" SIP header as follows:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para><emphasis>CISCO ATA</emphasis> - it has 4 pre-defined
			ringing types. The Alert-Info header must look like
			<quote>Alert-info: Bellcore-drX EOH</quote> where X can be
			between 1 and 4. Note that 1 is the phone default ringing tone.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para><emphasis>CISCO 7960</emphasis> - it has 2 pre-defined
			ringing types and the possibility of uploading new ones.
			The <quote>Alert-Info</quote> header must look like
			<quote>Alert-info: X EOH</quote> where X can be whatever number.
			When this header is present, the phones will not change the
			ringing tone, but the ringing pattern. Normally, the phone rings
			like [ring.........ring..........ring] where [ring] is the
			ringing tone; if the header is present, the ringing pattern will
			be [ring.ring.........ring.ring........]. So, to be able to hear
			some difference between the two patterns (and not only as length),
			its strongly recommended to have a highly asymmetric ringing type
			(as the pre-defined are not!!).
			</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para><emphasis>SNOM</emphasis> - The <quote>Alert-Info</quote>
			header must look like <quote>Alert-info: URL EOH"</quote> where
			URL can be a HTTP URL (for example) from where the phone can
			retrieve a ringing tone.
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>

	<section id="dependencies" xreflabel="Dependencies">
	<title>Dependencies</title>
	<section>
		<title>&osips; Modules</title>
		<para>
		The following modules must be loaded before this module:
                    <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis>tls_mgm</emphasis>.
			</para>
			</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Dependencies of external libraries</title>
		<para>
			&osips; TLS v1.0 support requires the following packages:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>openssl</emphasis> or
					<emphasis>libssl</emphasis> >= 0.9.6
				</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>openssl-dev</emphasis> or
					<emphasis>libssl-dev</emphasis>
				</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			&osips; TLS v1.1/1.2 support requires the following packages:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>openssl</emphasis> or
					<emphasis>libssl</emphasis> >= 1.0.1e
				</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>openssl-dev</emphasis> or
					<emphasis>libssl-dev</emphasis>
				</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>&osips; Exported parameters</title>
		<para>
		All these parameters can be used from the opensips.cfg file,
		to configure the behavior of &osips;-TLS.
		</para>

		<section id="param_listen" xreflabel="listen">
			<title><varname>listen</varname>=interface</title>
			<para>
			Not specific to TLS. Allows to specify the protocol
			(udp, tcp, tls), the IP address and the port where the
			listening server will be.
			</para>
			<example>
				<title>Set <varname>listen</varname> variable</title>
				<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
socket= tls:1.2.3.4:5061
...
				</programlisting>
			</example>
		</section>

		<section id="param_tls_port" xreflabel="tls_port">
			<title><varname>tls_port</varname> (integer)</title>
			<para>
			The default port to be used for all TLS related operation. Be 
			careful as the default port impacts both the SIP listening part 
			(if no port is defined in the TLS listeners) and the SIP sending 
			part (if the destination URI has no explicit port).
			</para>
			<para>
			If you want to change only the listening port for TLS, use the port
			option in the SIP listener defintion.
			</para>
			<para><emphasis>
				Default value is 5061.
			</emphasis></para>
			<example>
				<title>Set <varname>tls_port</varname> variable</title>
				<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("proto_tls", "tls_port", 5062)
...
				</programlisting>
			</example>
		</section>

	<section id="param_tls_crlf_pingpong" xreflabel="tls_crlf_pingpong">
		<title><varname>tls_crlf_pingpong</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
			Send CRLF pong (\r\n) to incoming CRLFCRLF ping messages over TLS.
			By default it is enabled (1).
		</para>
		<para>
		<emphasis>
			Default value is 1 (enabled).
		</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>tls_crlf_pingpong</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("proto_tls", "tls_crlf_pingpong", 0)
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="param_tls_crlf_drop" xreflabel="tls_crlf_drop">
		<title><varname>tls_crlf_drop</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
			Drop CRLF (\r\n) ping messages. When this parameter is enabled,
			the TLS layer drops packets that contains a single CRLF message.
			If a CRLFCRLF message is received, it is handled according to the
			<emphasis>tls_crlf_pingpong</emphasis> parameter.
		</para>
		<para>
		<emphasis>
			Default value is 0 (disabled).
		</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>tls_crlf_drop</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("proto_tls", "tls_crlf_drop", 1)
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	<section id="param_tls_max_msg_chunks" xreflabel="tls_max_msg_chunks">
		<title><varname>tls_max_msg_chunks</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
			The maximum number of chunks that a SIP message is expected to
			arrive via TLS. If a packet is received more fragmented than this,
			the connection is dropped (either the connection is very
			overloaded and this leads to high fragmentation - or we are the
			victim of an ongoing attack where the attacker is sending the
			traffic very fragmented in order to decrease server performance).
		</para>
		<para>
		<emphasis>
			Default value is 4.
		</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>tls_max_msg_chunks</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("proto_tls", "tls_max_msg_chunks", 8)
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	<section id="param_tls_cert_check_on_conn_reusage" xreflabel="cert_check_on_conn_reusage">
		<title><varname>cert_check_on_conn_reusage</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
		This parameter turns on or off the extra checking/matching of the
		TLS domain (SSL certificate) when comes to reusing an existing TLS
		connection. Without this extra check, only IP and port of the
		connections will be check (in order to re-use an existing connection).
		With this extra check, the connection to be reused must have the same
		SSL certificate as the one set for the current signaling operation.
		</para>
		<para>
		This checking is done only when comes to send SIP traffic via TLS and
		it is applied only against connections that were created / initiated 
		by OpenSIPS (as TLS client). Any accepte connection (as TLS server) will
		automatically match (the extra test will be skipped).
		</para>
		<para>
		<emphasis>
			Default value is 0 (disabled).
		</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>cert_check_on_conn_reusage</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("proto_tls", "cert_check_on_conn_reusage", 1)
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	<section id="param_tls_trace_destination" xreflabel="trace_destination">
		<title><varname>trace_destination</varname> (string)</title>
		<para>
			Trace destination as defined in the tracing module. Currently
		the only tracing module is <emphasis role="bold">proto_hep</emphasis>.
		Network events such as connect, accept and connection closed events
		shall be traced along with errors that could appear in the process.
		For each connection that is created an event containing information
		about the client and server certificates, master key and network layer
		information shall be sent.
		</para>
		<para>
			<emphasis role="bold">WARNING: </emphasis>A tracing module must be
			loaded in order for this parameter to work. (for example
			<emphasis role="bold">proto_hep</emphasis>).
		</para>
		<para>
		<emphasis>
			Default value is none(not defined).
		</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>trace_destination</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("proto_hep", "trace_destination", "[hep_dest]10.0.0.2;transport=tcp;version=3")

modparam("proto_tls", "trace_destination", "hep_dest")
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	<section id="param_trace_on" xreflabel="trace_on">
		<title><varname>trace_on</varname> (int)</title>
		<para>
			This controls whether tracing for tls is on or not. You still need to define
			<xref linkend="param_tls_trace_destination"/>in order to work, but this value will be
			controlled using mi function <xref linkend="mi_tls_trace"/>.
		</para>
		<emphasis>
			Default value is 0(tracing inactive).
		</emphasis>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>trace_on</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("proto_tls", "trace_on", 1)
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	<section id="param_trace_filter_route" xreflabel="trace_filter_route">
		<title><varname>trace_filter_route</varname> (string)</title>
		<para>
			Define the name of a route in which you can filter which connections will
			be trace and which connections won't be. In this route you will have
			information regarding source and destination ips and ports for the current
			connection. To disable tracing for a specific connection the last call in
			this route must be <emphasis role="bold">drop</emphasis>, any other exit
			mode resulting in tracing the current connection ( of course you still
			have to define a <xref linkend="param_tls_trace_destination"/> and trace must be
			on at the time this connection is opened.
		</para>
		<para>
			<emphasis role="bold">IMPORTANT</emphasis>
			Filtering on ip addresses and ports can be made using <emphasis role="bold">
			$si</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">$sp</emphasis> for matching
			either the entity that is connecting to &osips; or the entity to which
			&osips; is connecting. The name might be misleading (<emphasis role="bold">
				$si</emphasis> meaning the source ip if you read the docs) but in reality
			it is simply the socket other than the &osips; socket. In order to match
			&osips; interface (either the one that accepted the connection or the one
			that initiated a connection) <emphasis role="bold">$socket_in(ip)</emphasis> (ip) and
			<emphasis role="bold">$socket_in(port)</emphasis> (port) can be used.
		</para>

		<para>
			<emphasis role="bold">WARNING:</emphasis> IF <xref linkend="param_trace_on"/> is
			set to 0 or tracing is deactived via the mi command <xref linkend="mi_tls_trace"/>
			this route won't be called.
		</para>
		<emphasis>
			Default value is none(no route is set).
		</emphasis>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>trace_filter_route</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("proto_tls", "trace_filter_route", "tls_filter")
...
/* all tls connections will go through this route if tracing is activated
 * and a trace destination is defined */
route[tls_filter] {
	...
	/* all connections opened from/by ip 1.1.1.1:8000 will be traced
	   on interface 1.1.1.10:5060(opensips listener)
	   all the other connections won't be */
	 if ( $si == "1.1.1.1" &amp;&amp; $sp == 8000 &amp;&amp;
		$socket_in(ip) == "1.1.1.10"  &amp;&amp; $socket_in(port) == 5060)
		exit;
	else
		drop;
}
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	<section id="param_tls_handshake_timeout" xreflabel="tls_handshake_timeout">
		<title><varname>tls_handshake_timeout</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
		Sets the timeout (in milliseconds) for the SSL handshake sequence to complete.
			It may be necessary to increase this value when using a CPU intensive cipher
			for the connection to allow time for keys to be generated and processed.
		</para>
		<para>
		The timeout is invoked during acceptance of a new connection (inbound) and
			during the wait period when a new session is being initiated (outbound).
		</para>
		<para><emphasis>
			Default value is 100.
		</emphasis></para>
		<example>
			<title>Set <varname>tls_handshake_timeout</varname> variable</title>
			<programlisting format="linespecific">

param("proto_tls", "tls_handshake_timeout", 200) # number of milliseconds

			</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	<section id="param_tls_send_timeout" xreflabel="tls_send_timeout">
		<title><varname>tls_send_timeout</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
			Sets the timeout (in milliseconds) for the send operations to complete
		</para>
		<para>
			The send timeout is invoked for all TLS write operations, excluding
			the handshake process (see: tls_handshake_timeout)
		</para>
		<para><emphasis>
			Default value is 100.
		</emphasis></para>
		<example>
			<title>Set <varname>tls_send_timeout</varname> variable</title>
			<programlisting format="linespecific">

param("proto_tls", "tls_send_timeout", 200) # number of milliseconds

			</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	</section>


	<section id="exported_mi_functions" xreflabel="Exported MI Functions">
	<title>Exported MI Functions</title>

		<section id="mi_tls_trace" xreflabel="tls_trace">
			<title>
			<function moreinfo="none">tls_trace</function>
			</title>

			<para>
			</para>

			<para>
			Name: <emphasis>tls_trace</emphasis>
			</para>

			<para>Parameters: </para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>trace_mode(optional): set tls tracing on and off. This parameter
						can be missing and the command will show the current tracing
						status for this module( on or off );
						Possible values:
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para> on </para></listitem>
							<listitem><para> off </para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>
			MI FIFO Command Format:
			</para>
			<programlisting  format="linespecific">
			opensips-cli -x mi tls_trace on
			</programlisting>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
