<para><emphasis>flags (string, optional)</emphasis></para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
	<para>
	<emphasis>'b' (no Branches)</emphasis> - this flag controls how
	the &reg_lookup_f; function processes multiple contacts.
	If there are
	multiple contacts for the given username in usrloc and this
	flag is not set, Request-URI will be overwritten with the
	highest-q rated contact and the rest will be appended to
	sip_msg structure and can be later used by tm for forking. If
	the flag is set, only Request-URI will be overwritten
	with the highest-q rated contact and the rest will be left
	unprocessed.
	</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
	<para>
	<emphasis>'B' (to Branches only)</emphasis> - this flags forces
	all found contacts to be uploaded only as branches (in the
	destination set) and not at all in the R-URI of the
	current message.  Using this option allows the &reg_lookup_f; function to
	also be used in the context of a SIP reply.
	</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
	<para>
	<emphasis>'r' (bRanch lookup)</emphasis> - this flag enables
	searching through existing branches for aor's and expanding
	them to contacts. For example, you have got AOR A in your
	ruri but you also want to forward your calls to AOR B. In order
	to do this, you must put AOR B in a branch, and if this flag
	enabled, the function will also expand AOR B to contacts,
	which will be put back into the branches. The AOR's that were
	in branches before the function call shall be removed.
	</para>

	<para>
	<emphasis role='bold'>WARNING: </emphasis>
	<emphasis>if you want this flag activated,
	the 'b' (no Branches) flag must not be set, because by setting
	that flag you won't allow &reg_lookup_f; to write in a branch.</emphasis>
	</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
	<para>
	<emphasis>'m' (Method filtering)</emphasis> - setting this flag
	will enable contact filtering based on the supported methods
	listed in the "Allow" header field during registration.
	Contacts which did not present an "Allow" header field during
	registration are assumed to support all standard SIP methods.
	</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
	<para>
	<emphasis>'u' (User-Agent filtering)</emphasis> - this flag
	enables regexp filtering by user-agent. It's useful with
	enabled append_branches parameter. Regexp must follow
	the 'u' flag and must use format like 'u/regexp/'.
	</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
	<para>
	<emphasis>'i' (Case insensitive search)</emphasis> - this flag
	enables case insensitive filtering for the 'u' flag.
	</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
	<para>
	<emphasis>'e' (Use extended regexp)</emphasis> - this flag
	enables using of extended regexp format for the 'u' flag.
	</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
	<para>
	<emphasis>'g' (Global lookup)</emphasis> - this flag
	is only relevant with federated user location clustering. If
	set, the &reg_lookup_f; function will not only perform the classic
	in-memory "search-AoR-and-push-branches" operation, but will
	also perform a metadata lookup and append an additional branch
	for each returned result. The "in-memory branches" correspond
	to local contacts (current location), while the "metadata
	branches" correspond to contacts available on one or more of
	the remaining locations of the platform.
	</para>
	<para>
	The AoR metadata consists of the minimally required information
	in order for one of the VoIP platform's locations (data
	centers) to advertise the presence of a locally registered AoR
	for the global platform. Specifically, this consists of two
	pieces of information:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
		<para>
			the AoR (e.g. "vladimir@federation-cluster")
		</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		<para>
			the home IP (e.g. "10.0.0.223")
		</para>
	</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
	<para>
	<emphasis>'yXXXXX' (Max pinging latency)</emphasis> - maximally
	accepted contact pinging latency (microseconds). Contacts of an
	AoR with a higher latency will be discarded during &reg_lookup_f;.
	</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
	<para>
	<emphasis>'Y' (Sort by pinging latency)</emphasis> - contacts
	will be picked in ascending order of their last successful
	pinging latency (fastest ping -> slowest ping). This flag may
	work together with the "y" flag.
	</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
