<!-- Module User's Guide -->

<chapter>
	
	<title>&adminguide;</title>
	
	<section>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<para>
		This module does Call-ID mangling to bypass Asterisk PBX chan_sip spiral
		detection.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Asterisk PBX chan_sip</title>
			<para>
			Asterisk is a telephony switching and private branch exchange.
			Its chan_sip module handles SIP support. That module features
			loop/spiral detection solely based on recognising a currently
			used Call-ID.
			</para>
			<para>
			While that loop detection helps against unwanted loops, it
			does complicate creating proper billing records. The detection
			merges what should be two calls (customer X calling out and
			customer Y getting called) into a single call.
			</para>
			<para>
			The workaround is to ensure that the Call-IDs are mangled in
			one direction. That way the loop detection is bypassed.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Alternative workarounds</title>
			<para>
			A different solution would be to use the b2bua module,
			or the callid hiding feature of the dialog module.
			</para>
			<para>
			However, both solutions require the dialog module to keep state
			of the open dialogs. This module is more lightweight.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Caveats</title>
			<para>
			Attempting to combine this with the pua_dialoginfo module may
			produce unexpected results.
			</para>
			<para>
			The intent of this module is NOT to hide the callid. On the
			contrary, by only prefixing it with a magic value, the SIP
			messages can be easily matched together.
			</para>
			<para>
			If your proxy speaks to a second &osips; server that uses this
			module, you'll need to give both a distinct
			<quote>callid_mangling_prefix</quote>. This magic string will
			be considered when deciding in which manner the Call-ID should
			be rewritten.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
	<title>Dependencies</title>
	<section>
		<title>&osips; Modules</title>
		<para>
		The following modules must be loaded before this module:
			<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				The rr module. Obviously, this proxy should stay in the
				path of the dialog to be able to rewrite the Call-IDs.
				Spiral uses the ftag= Route parameter to determine the
				direction of in-dialog SIP messages.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>
	</section>

	<section>
	<title>Exported Parameters</title>
	
	<section>
		<title><varname>callid_mangling_prefix</varname> (string)</title>
		<para>
		The string to use as a prefix when rewriting Call-IDs.
		</para>
		<para>
		Look at the SIP RFC for legal character combinations.
		RFC4475 hints which rare characters are still legal.
		</para>
		<para>
		The default is <quote>~{}~</quote> since it is not used by the
		Asterisk PBX chan_sip generated Call-IDs. And it has been tested
		to work with chan_sip.
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>callid_mangling_prefix</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
		
...
modparam("spiral", "callid_mangling_prefix", "MAGIC_CALLID-")
...

</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	</section>

</chapter>
