<!-- Module User's Guide -->

<chapter>

    <title>&adminguide;</title>

    <section id="overview" xreflabel="Overview">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
	The <emphasis>clusterer_controller</emphasis> module provides
	automatic peer discovery and topology management for the
	<emphasis>clusterer</emphasis> module via authenticated, encrypted
	UDP multicast. It eliminates the need for static node configuration
	or a database — nodes discover each other automatically at startup
	and the cluster topology is maintained dynamically at runtime.
    </para>
    <para>
	When <varname>use_controller=1</varname> is set in the
	<emphasis>clusterer</emphasis> module, the
	<emphasis>clusterer_controller</emphasis> module takes over all
	topology management: it allocates unique node IDs, discovers peer
	BIN socket addresses, and calls the clusterer internal API to add
	or remove nodes as they join or leave the cluster.
    </para>
    <para>
	By default (<varname>manage_shtags=1</varname>), the module also
	provides fully automatic sharing tag failover. The controller
	master node is the single decision point for which node holds the
	active tag — no event routes, MI commands, or
	<varname>seed_fallback_interval</varname> configuration is needed.
	Sharing tags are forced to backup at startup regardless of the
	<emphasis>=active</emphasis> config value, and the active tag is
	claimed by the controller master automatically when the cluster
	forms or when the active node departs. An operator can override this
	automatic allocation and pin the active tag to a chosen node with the
	<function>cc_shtag_force</function> MI command, reverting to automatic
	allocation with <function>cc_shtag_auto</function>.
    </para>
    <para>
	The minimal configuration per node is a single multicast group
	address. No IP addresses, node IDs, BIN URLs, or sharing tag
	management scripts need to be hardcoded or maintained. Any number
	of nodes can join or leave without any configuration change on
	the remaining nodes.
    </para>
    </section>

    <section id="protocol" xreflabel="Protocol">
    <title>Discovery Protocol</title>
    <para>
	All traffic uses UDP multicast to the configured
	<varname>multicast</varname> address and port. Clusters are kept
	apart in two independent ways: by the multicast endpoint (two
	clusters may use different IP addresses, or the same address with
	different UDP ports), and by the <varname>id</varname>
	(<varname>cluster_id</varname>) carried in the cleartext of every
	packet. A node silently ignores any packet whose cluster_id differs
	from its own, so several clusters can safely share one multicast
	group and port. Two clusters merge only if they share
	<emphasis>all</emphasis> of the multicast address, the UDP port, the
	cluster_id and the password — i.e. they are configured identically,
	which is the operator's responsibility to avoid.
    </para>
    <para>
	Every packet is encrypted and authenticated with an AEAD —
	AES-256-GCM by default, or XChaCha20-Poly1305 when the module is built
	against libsodium (see the <emphasis>Security Architecture</emphasis>
	section). Two distinct encryption keys are used depending on the
	communication phase:
	<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">Bootstrap key</emphasis> — derived from
		the configured <varname>password</varname> with a memory-hard KDF
		(<emphasis>scrypt</emphasis> N=2<superscript>16</superscript>, r=8,
		p=1, or <emphasis>Argon2id</emphasis> in the libsodium build, with a
		per-cluster salt), so a password captured from a bootstrap packet
		cannot be brute-forced cheaply offline. Derived once at startup.
		Used for the admission handshake (JOIN_REQ, KEY_GRANT, JOIN_REJECT)
		and the split-brain MASTER_BEACON — traffic that must be readable
		before a session key exists, or by masters holding different
		session keys.
	    </para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">Session key</emphasis> — derived via
		HKDF-SHA256 from the password and a 32-byte master salt
		generated once when the cluster first bootstraps. All normal
		cluster traffic uses this key. It is preserved across master
		changes (a new master reuses the key every member already
		holds), so failover needs no re-keying.
	    </para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
	Each packet wire format begins with a 2-byte magic value
	identifying the key type and a 2-byte cluster_id, both in cleartext
	(the magic and cluster_id must be readable before decryption to
	select the key and to filter foreign clusters), followed by a random
	AEAD nonce (12 bytes for AES-256-GCM, 24 for XChaCha20-Poly1305) and
	the ciphertext. The magic and cluster_id are additionally bound into
	the authentication tag as AAD, so they cannot be altered undetected.
	Only the payload is encrypted; the authenticated plaintext begins with
	a 1-byte packet type and a 4-byte monotonic sequence number used for
	replay protection. A 16-byte authentication tag follows the ciphertext.
	Packets for a different cluster_id are dropped before decryption;
	packets encrypted with a different password fail authentication and
	are silently discarded.
    </para>
    <para>
	The following packet types are defined:
	<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">ALIVE</emphasis> — periodic heartbeat
		sent by every active node every <varname>query_time</varname>
		seconds. Carries the sender IP, its X25519 public key (so peers
		can prepare for key agreement) and a small descriptor of the
		sender's consistency-critical settings
		(<varname>manage_shtags</varname>,
		<varname>master_stickiness</varname>,
		<varname>query_time</varname>) used for configuration-drift
		detection (see Security Architecture). Encrypted with the session
		key.
	    </para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">JOIN_REQ</emphasis> — sent at startup
		by a new node, carrying its IP, BIN socket list, X25519
		ephemeral public key, and a 16-byte random join nonce.
		Encrypted with the bootstrap key so it can be sent before a
		session key exists.
	    </para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">MEMBER_LIST</emphasis> — sent by the
		master in response to a JOIN_REQ, carrying the member count, the
		operator-forced sharing-tag holder node_id (0 = automatic), and
		the full peer IP list so the joining node can participate in
		elections. Only accepted from the current master (except during
		initial join when no master is yet known).
	    </para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">NODE_ASSIGN</emphasis> — sent by the
		master to multicast, allocating a node_id and BIN socket
		record for a joining node. All cluster members receive and
		apply it.
	    </para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">GOODBYE</emphasis> — sent on graceful
		shutdown so peers can remove the node immediately without
		waiting for timeout. Uses the sender's monotonic sequence
		counter to prevent forgery.
	    </para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">MASTER_ALIVE</emphasis> — keepalive
		sent by the master every 1 second (independent of
		<varname>query_time</varname>). Used by all peers to detect
		master failure quickly (3-second timeout). Encrypted with
		the session key.
	    </para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">KEY_GRANT</emphasis> — unicast response
		to a JOIN_REQ, sent by the master directly to the joining
		node. Contains the master's X25519 public key, the original
		join nonce, and the master salt wrapped with a per-exchange
		key derived from ECDH(master_priv, joiner_pub) + password +
		join_nonce via HKDF-SHA256. Encrypted with the bootstrap key.
	    </para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">KEY_HANDOFF</emphasis> — unicast packet
		sent by the outgoing master on graceful shutdown to the
		next-highest-IP peer, delivering the master salt so that peer
		can become the new master without a full re-join cycle.
		Encrypted with the session key.
	    </para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">JOIN_REJECT</emphasis> — sent by the
		master to a joining node whose JOIN_REQ repeatedly fails
		authentication (wrong password). After
		<emphasis>CC_JOIN_FAIL_LIMIT</emphasis> (3) consecutive
		bootstrap-key decryption failures from the same source IP the
		master sends a JOIN_REJECT to that IP. Encrypted with the
		bootstrap key so it cannot be forged by a node that does not
		know the cluster password. The joining node logs a critical
		error and shuts down OpenSIPS on receipt.
	    </para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">MASTER_BEACON</emphasis> — a master-only
		announcement multicast every few MASTER_ALIVE ticks, carrying this
		partition's member count. Unlike MASTER_ALIVE it is encrypted with
		the <emphasis>bootstrap</emphasis> key, so it is readable even by a
		master that holds a different session key. This is how a split
		brain between two independently bootstrapped partitions is detected
		and merged (see <emphasis>Master Election</emphasis>).
	    </para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </para>
    </section>

    <section id="election" xreflabel="Master Election">
    <title>Master Election</title>
    <para>
	Each cluster has three roles: <emphasis role="bold">master</emphasis>
	(the active coordinator), <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> (the
	standby promoted when the master fails, always the highest-IP
	non-master) and <emphasis role="bold">member</emphasis>. The election
	uses a quantized time window so that all nodes evaluate the same
	eligible peer set and reach the same result deterministically. No NTP
	synchronisation between nodes is required for correct election results.
    </para>
    <para>
	The <varname>master_stickiness</varname> parameter (default 1) controls
	whether a live master is kept when a higher-IP node joins. With
	stickiness enabled, the master stays put and the higher-IP joiner
	becomes the backup, minimising handovers; with stickiness disabled the
	highest-IP node always becomes master. In either mode two live masters
	are reconciled deterministically (see <emphasis>Split-brain
	handling</emphasis> below). See the <varname>master_stickiness</varname>
	parameter for details.
    </para>
    <para>
	Only the master handles JOIN_REQ packets, allocates node_ids, and
	sends NODE_ASSIGN and MEMBER_LIST packets. Non-master nodes are
	passive during join events. A joining node receives the current
	session key from the master (via KEY_GRANT) and joins as a member or
	backup; it never seizes mastership during the join handshake.
    </para>
    <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">Preserved session key:</emphasis> the session key
	is generated once, when the first node bootstraps the cluster, and is
	then preserved across every master change. A new master does not
	re-key; because every member already holds the key (obtained when it
	joined), master transitions require no re-keying and no re-JOIN cycle.
    </para>
    <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">Fast master failure detection:</emphasis>
	the master sends MASTER_ALIVE packets every 1 second. All non-master
	peers maintain a 3-second watchdog timer that fires if no MASTER_ALIVE
	is received. On expiry the silent master is aged out of the election
	window and each peer immediately re-elects, promoting the backup
	(highest-IP survivor) — which already holds the session key, so it
	starts serving within one keepalive interval.
    </para>
    <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">Graceful master handoff:</emphasis> when the
	current master shuts down cleanly, it sends a KEY_HANDOFF packet
	directly to the next-highest-IP peer before sending GOODBYE to
	multicast. This confirms the master salt to the incoming master so it
	can assume control immediately.
    </para>
    <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">Split-brain handling.</emphasis> A split brain
	(more than one node believing it is master) is prevented and, if it
	still occurs, healed by three cooperating mechanisms:
	<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">Prevention at join time.</emphasis> When
		several nodes start simultaneously they all exchange
		(bootstrap-decryptable) JOIN_REQs and thus learn about each other.
		At the join deadline, a node that has seen a higher-IP node also
		still joining defers its own self-promotion (for a few bounded
		rounds) and joins that node instead, so only the highest-IP starter
		becomes master and no independent-key lone masters are created.
	    </para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">Same-key yield.</emphasis> Two masters that
		share a session key (for example after a network partition heals)
		can read each other's MASTER_ALIVE; the lower-IP master immediately
		yields to the higher-IP one.
	    </para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">Divergent-key merge.</emphasis> Two masters
		that were bootstrapped independently hold different session keys and
		so cannot read each other's MASTER_ALIVE. Each therefore emits a
		MASTER_BEACON encrypted with the shared bootstrap key. On hearing a
		beacon from a superior partition — larger member count, ties broken
		by higher IP — a node abandons its partition, re-joins the superior
		master and adopts its session key, converging the whole cluster onto
		a single master and key.
	    </para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </para>
    </section>

    <section id="security" xreflabel="Security">
    <title>Security Architecture</title>
    <para>
	The module uses a two-phase key agreement to provide forward
	secrecy and replay protection for all cluster traffic.
    </para>
    <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">Payload encryption and header binding:</emphasis>
	every packet's payload is sealed with an AEAD. The 2-byte magic (a key
	selector that must be readable before decryption) and the 2-byte
	cluster_id that precede the nonce are cleartext framing, but they are
	bound into the AEAD tag as additional authenticated data (AAD): a
	captured packet cannot be re-stamped with a different cluster_id and
	still authenticate, which matters when two clusters share one multicast
	group and password. A node also drops any packet whose cluster_id does
	not match its own <emphasis>before</emphasis> attempting decryption, so
	foreign-cluster traffic on the group never counts as an authentication
	failure.
    </para>
    <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">Crypto suite (selected at build time):</emphasis>
	by default the module uses <emphasis>AES-256-GCM</emphasis> (12-byte
	nonce) for the payload AEAD and <emphasis>scrypt</emphasis>
	(N=2<superscript>16</superscript>, r=8, p=1) for the bootstrap-key
	derivation, through WolfSSL. If <emphasis>libsodium</emphasis> is
	detected on the build host, the module is compiled instead with
	<emphasis>XChaCha20-Poly1305</emphasis> (24-byte nonce, whose 192-bit
	nonce space removes any random-nonce collision concern) and
	<emphasis>Argon2id</emphasis>. The two wire formats are not
	interoperable, so every node in a cluster must be built with the same
	suite; the active suite is reported in the startup log
	(<emphasis>crypto=...</emphasis>).
    </para>
    <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">Phase 1 — bootstrap (JOIN_REQ /
	KEY_GRANT):</emphasis> each worker process generates an ephemeral
	X25519 keypair on startup. When joining, the node sends its
	public key and a 16-byte random join nonce in the JOIN_REQ,
	encrypted with the bootstrap key (a memory-hard KDF of the password —
	scrypt, or Argon2id in the libsodium build). The
	master responds with a KEY_GRANT encrypted with the same bootstrap
	key, containing its own public key, the echoed join nonce, and
	the master salt wrapped with a per-exchange key derived via
	HKDF-SHA256 from:
	<programlisting format="linespecific">IKM = ECDH(master_priv, joiner_pub) || password || join_nonce</programlisting>
	This ensures that even if the password is compromised, previously
	recorded exchanges cannot be decrypted without both the ephemeral
	private key and the per-exchange join nonce.
    </para>
    <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">Phase 2 — session (all other
	packets):</emphasis> once the master salt is known, all nodes
	derive the session key as:
	<programlisting format="linespecific">session_key = HKDF-SHA256(IKM=password, salt=master_salt, info="cc-session-key")</programlisting>
	The session key is generated once, when the first node bootstraps the
	cluster, and preserved across every master change: a new master reuses
	the key that every member already holds, so master transitions require
	no re-keying. All normal cluster traffic (ALIVE, MEMBER_LIST,
	NODE_ASSIGN, GOODBYE, MASTER_ALIVE, KEY_HANDOFF) is encrypted with this
	key.
    </para>
    <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">Replay protection:</emphasis> each sender
	maintains a monotonically increasing 32-bit sequence number
	embedded in the authenticated plaintext of every session-key
	packet. Each receiver tracks the last accepted sequence number
	per source IP and rejects any packet whose sequence is not
	strictly greater than the last accepted value. Sequence counters
	are reset to zero whenever the session key is (re)derived — at cluster
	bootstrap and when a joiner adopts the key via KEY_GRANT/KEY_HANDOFF —
	and on peer restart detection (JOIN_REQ received from a known IP resets
	that peer's counter; MEMBER_LIST upsert resets all listed peers).
	This protection does not depend on clock synchronisation.
    </para>
    <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">Rate limiting:</emphasis> a per-source rate
	limiter (256 slots, 20 packets/second limit) is applied before any
	decryption attempt. This prevents CPU exhaustion from packet floods
	directed at the multicast group.
    </para>
    <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">Join authentication and rejection:</emphasis>
	the master tracks consecutive bootstrap-key decryption failures per
	source IP in a small worker-local table
	(<emphasis>CC_JOIN_FAIL_TABLE_SZ</emphasis> = 8 slots). When any
	source IP accumulates <emphasis>CC_JOIN_FAIL_LIMIT</emphasis> (3)
	consecutive failures — indicating a node attempting to join with the
	wrong password — the master sends an encrypted JOIN_REJECT packet
	and stops responding to further JOIN_REQs from that IP.
    </para>
    <para>
	On the joining side, a received JOIN_REJECT is only acted on while
	the node is still in the initial join phase
	(<emphasis>CC_NODE_NEW</emphasis> state) and is addressed to this
	node; an already-active cluster member ignores any JOIN_REJECT
	unconditionally, so a node with the correct password can never be
	evicted by a peer.
    </para>
    <para>
	A node joining with the <emphasis>wrong</emphasis> password cannot
	decrypt the JOIN_REJECT (it is encrypted with the master's bootstrap
	key), so it relies on a self-contained signal instead: while joining
	it counts packets received from other peers that it cannot decrypt.
	If, at the join deadline, the node is still unjoined and has seen
	<emphasis>CC_JOIN_FAIL_LIMIT</emphasis> or more such undecryptable
	packets, it concludes that a cluster it cannot authenticate to exists
	on the group and shuts down OpenSIPS with a critical log message —
	rather than promoting itself into a lone, split-brain master (which,
	with managed sharing tags, would create a duplicate active tag). This
	counter is reset the moment a KEY_GRANT is successfully processed, so
	a legitimate joiner that briefly saw an undecryptable packet before
	receiving its key is never affected.
    </para>
    <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">Rogue traffic isolation:</emphasis> a node
	requests a re-key in response to an undecryptable session-key packet
	only when that packet came from its current master (a legitimate key
	rotation). Undecryptable session packets from any other source — for
	example a wrong-password or malicious node broadcasting on the
	multicast group — are ignored, so such traffic cannot drive the
	cluster into a re-JOIN churn.
    </para>
    <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">Peer table exhaustion defence:</emphasis> the
	peer table is bounded at <emphasis>CC_MAX_PEERS</emphasis> (256)
	entries. When the table is full, the master rejects JOIN_REQ
	packets from unknown IPs with a JOIN_REJECT response. Known peers
	that are reconnecting after a restart continue to be admitted
	regardless of the table count, since they already own a slot.
	This prevents an attacker with the cluster password from exhausting
	the peer table by flooding JOIN_REQs from spoofed source addresses.
    </para>
    <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">Configuration-consistency enforcement:</emphasis>
	all nodes of a cluster must use identical consistency-critical settings
	(<varname>manage_shtags</varname>, <varname>master_stickiness</varname>
	and <varname>query_time</varname>); a per-node mismatch would otherwise
	cause silent, inconsistent failover and sharing-tag behaviour (for
	example, a master with <varname>manage_shtags=0</varname> would leave no
	node holding the active tag). Each node advertises these effective
	settings in its ALIVE heartbeat and in its JOIN_REQ, so mismatches are
	detected. What happens then is controlled by the
	<varname>on_config_mismatch</varname> modparam:
	<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis>reject</emphasis> (default) - when a node tries to
		join an established cluster (a master is alive) with different
		settings, the master logs the attempt and returns a JOIN_REJECT;
		the joining node logs the offending settings and shuts down, so a
		misconfigured node never joins.
	    </para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis>warn</emphasis> - the node is allowed to join, but any
		peer that observes a different value logs a single loud
		<emphasis>CONFIG MISMATCH</emphasis> warning (repeated only if the
		peer's advertised configuration changes, cleared once it matches).
	    </para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis>adopt</emphasis> - the joining node adopts the running
		cluster's (master's) settings at runtime and continues; the
		adopted values are what <function>cc_list_config</function>
		reports.
	    </para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	This turns an easy-to-miss misconfiguration into an obvious log line, a
	refused join, or a self-correction rather than a hard-to-diagnose HA
	failure.
    </para>
    </section>

    <section id="dependencies" xreflabel="Dependencies">
    <title>Dependencies</title>
    <section>
	<title>&osips; Modules</title>
	<para>
	The following modules are required by this module:
	    <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		    <emphasis>proto_bin</emphasis> — required so that
		    BIN listeners are registered and available for
		    discovery when <emphasis>clusterer_controller</emphasis>
		    initialises and scans the proto_bin listener list.
		</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		    <emphasis>clusterer</emphasis> — required with
		    <varname>use_controller=1</varname> set, so that
		    the clusterer internal API
		    (<function>load_clusterer_ctrl_binds</function>) is
		    exported and available at initialisation time.
		</para>
		</listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<para>
	    Both dependencies are declared in the module's
	    <varname>dep_export_t</varname>. &osips; will refuse to
	    start if either dependency is not satisfied. This does
	    <emphasis>not</emphasis> imply that the modules must appear
	    in a particular order in the configuration file — &osips;
	    resolves the dependency at runtime and will initialize the
	    required modules first regardless of
	    <function>loadmodule</function> order.
	</para>
	<para>
	    All other modules that use the clusterer interface
	    (<emphasis>tm</emphasis>, <emphasis>dialog</emphasis>,
	    <emphasis>dispatcher</emphasis>, <emphasis>usrloc</emphasis>
	    etc.) may be loaded in any order relative to
	    <emphasis>clusterer_controller</emphasis>. The clusterer
	    module automatically creates a cluster stub when
	    <varname>use_controller=1</varname> is set and a module
	    attempts to register a capability for an unknown cluster.
	</para>
    </section>

    <section>
	<title>External Libraries or Applications</title>
	<para>
	The following libraries must be installed:
	    <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		    <emphasis>tls_wolfssl</emphasis> — the
		    <emphasis>clusterer_controller</emphasis> module links
		    statically against the WolfSSL library built by the
		    <emphasis>tls_wolfssl</emphasis> module
		    (<emphasis>modules/tls_wolfssl/lib/lib/libwolfssl.a</emphasis>).
		    WolfSSL provides AES-256-GCM authenticated encryption,
		    X25519 ECDH key agreement, HKDF-SHA256 key derivation,
		    the scrypt password KDF, and SHA-256. The <emphasis>tls_wolfssl</emphasis> module
		    must be present in the source tree; its static library
		    is built automatically as a dependency if not already
		    present.
		</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		    <emphasis>libsodium</emphasis> (optional) — if the build host
		    has libsodium development files (detected via
		    <function>pkg-config</function>), the module is compiled with
		    the stronger crypto suite: XChaCha20-Poly1305 for the payload
		    AEAD and Argon2id for the bootstrap-key derivation, in place of
		    AES-256-GCM and scrypt. X25519 ECDH and HKDF continue to use
		    WolfSSL. libsodium is linked dynamically, so each target host
		    then also needs the libsodium runtime package (for example
		    <emphasis>libsodium23</emphasis>). Because the two suites produce
		    incompatible wire formats, every node in a cluster must be built
		    the same way; the active suite is printed in the startup log.
		</para>
		</listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	</para>
    </section>
    </section>

    <section id="exported_parameters" xreflabel="Exported Parameters">
    <title>Exported Parameters</title>

	<section id="param_cluster" xreflabel="cluster">
	<title><varname>cluster</varname> (string)</title>
	<para>
	    Define a cluster to participate in. The value is a
	    comma-separated key=value string with the following fields:
	    <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		    <emphasis role="bold">id</emphasis> (required) —
		    positive integer cluster identifier, must match the
		    <varname>cluster_id</varname> used by clusterer
		    consumers (dialog, usrloc, dispatcher, etc.).
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		    <emphasis role="bold">multicast</emphasis> (required)
		    — IPv4 multicast address and UDP port in the form
		    <emphasis>A.B.C.D:PORT</emphasis>. The address must
		    be in the 224.0.0.0/4 range.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		    <emphasis role="bold">password</emphasis> (optional)
		    — AES-256 encryption key material. All nodes in the
		    same cluster must use the same password. Falls back
		    to the global <varname>password</varname> modparam
		    if not set.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		    <emphasis role="bold">bin_socket</emphasis>
		    (optional) — BIN socket to advertise for this
		    cluster, in the form
		    <emphasis>bin:IP:PORT</emphasis>. Required when
		    multiple clusters are defined. When only one cluster
		    is defined and only one BIN socket exists, the
		    socket is auto-detected from the
		    <emphasis>proto_bin</emphasis> listeners.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		    <emphasis role="bold">manage_shtags</emphasis>
		    (optional) — per-cluster override for the global
		    <varname>manage_shtags</varname> modparam. Set to
		    <emphasis>1</emphasis> to enable automatic sharing
		    tag failover for this cluster, or
		    <emphasis>0</emphasis> to disable it. When omitted,
		    the global <varname>manage_shtags</varname> value
		    applies, regardless of the order in which
		    <varname>cluster</varname> and
		    <varname>manage_shtags</varname> modparams appear
		    in the config file.
		</para></listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<para>
	    This parameter may be set multiple times to participate in
	    multiple clusters simultaneously. Each cluster runs its own
	    independent worker process.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis>No default value. At least one cluster must be
	    defined.</emphasis>
	</para>
	<example>
	    <title>Set <varname>cluster</varname> parameter — single cluster</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster",
    "id=1,multicast=239.0.90.1:3333")
...
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	<example>
	    <title>Set <varname>cluster</varname> parameter — multiple clusters</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster",
    "id=1,multicast=239.0.90.1:3333,bin_socket=bin:10.0.1.10:5566")
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster",
    "id=2,multicast=239.0.90.2:3333,bin_socket=bin:10.0.2.10:5566")
...
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	</section>

	<section id="param_my_ip" xreflabel="my_ip">
	<title><varname>my_ip</varname> (string)</title>
	<para>
	    Explicitly set the local IPv4 address used by the controller
	    for its own node identity and master election. This is the IP
	    that the controller advertises to peers in JOIN_REQ and
	    NODE_ASSIGN packets and uses for the highest-IP master
	    election algorithm.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Note: this parameter controls the controller's identity only.
	    The BIN socket address advertised to clusterer peers is
	    discovered separately from the <emphasis>proto_bin</emphasis>
	    listener list and is independent of this setting. Do not
	    confuse <varname>my_ip</varname> with the BIN socket IP
	    defined by the <emphasis>socket=bin:IP:PORT</emphasis> core
	    parameter.
	</para>
	<para>
	    When set, the module walks the interface list to find which
	    local interface owns this address and uses that interface for
	    multicast traffic. Startup fails if no local interface owns
	    the given address.
	</para>
	<para>
	    The module supports three identity resolution modes depending
	    on which modparams are provided:
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Mode 1 — my_ip set:</emphasis>
	    The given IP is used directly. The owning interface is
	    resolved automatically from the system interface list.
	    Use this mode on multi-homed hosts where you want to
	    pin the controller identity to a specific IP.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Mode 2 — interface set, my_ip not set:</emphasis>
	    The first IPv4 address on the named interface is used as
	    the controller identity IP. A warning is logged if the
	    interface has multiple IPv4 addresses.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Mode 3 — neither set (default):</emphasis>
	    A throw-away UDP socket is connected to the multicast
	    group and <function>getsockname()</function> is called
	    to determine which source IP the kernel would select.
	    The interface name is resolved from the returned IP.
	    Suitable for single-homed hosts.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis>Default: auto-detected (Mode 3).</emphasis>
	</para>
	<example>
	    <title>Set <varname>my_ip</varname> parameter</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("clusterer_controller", "my_ip", "10.22.23.191")
...
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	</section>

	<section id="param_interface" xreflabel="interface">
	<title><varname>interface</varname> (string)</title>
	<para>
	    Explicitly set the network interface name to use for
	    multicast traffic (e.g. <emphasis>eth0</emphasis>,
	    <emphasis>enp6s18</emphasis>). The module takes the first
	    IPv4 address assigned to this interface as the controller's
	    identity IP. This corresponds to Mode 2 described in the
	    <varname>my_ip</varname> parameter documentation above.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Like <varname>my_ip</varname>, this parameter affects the
	    controller's own identity only and has no effect on the
	    BIN socket addresses advertised to clusterer peers.
	</para>
	<para>
	    If the interface has more than one IPv4 address, a warning
	    is logged and the first address (in the order returned by
	    the kernel) is used. Set <varname>my_ip</varname> explicitly
	    to avoid ambiguity on multi-address interfaces.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Ignored if <varname>my_ip</varname> is also set —
	    <varname>my_ip</varname> takes precedence.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis>Default: auto-detected (Mode 3 — see
	    <varname>my_ip</varname>).</emphasis>
	</para>
	<example>
	    <title>Set <varname>interface</varname> parameter</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("clusterer_controller", "interface", "eth0")
...
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	</section>

	<section id="param_query_time" xreflabel="query_time">
	<title><varname>query_time</varname> (integer)</title>
	<para>
	    How often (in seconds) each active node sends an ALIVE
	    heartbeat to the multicast group. This value also controls
	    the election window
	    (<emphasis>3 × query_time</emphasis>) and the peer purge
	    window (<emphasis>6 × query_time</emphasis>).
	</para>
	<para>
	    Smaller values mean faster failure detection but higher
	    multicast traffic. Valid range: 1–60.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis>Default value is <quote>5</quote>.</emphasis>
	</para>
	<example>
	    <title>Set <varname>query_time</varname> parameter</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("clusterer_controller", "query_time", 5)
...
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	</section>

	<section id="param_password" xreflabel="password">
	<title><varname>password</varname> (string)</title>
	<para>
	    Global default encryption password for all clusters. All
	    nodes in a cluster must use the same password. The password
	    serves two purposes:
	    <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		    <emphasis role="bold">Bootstrap key</emphasis> —
		    the password is stretched with <emphasis>scrypt</emphasis>
		    (memory-hard, per-cluster salt) to encrypt JOIN_REQ and
		    KEY_GRANT packets during the initial key exchange phase
		    before a session key is established.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		    <emphasis role="bold">Session key material</emphasis> —
		    the password is fed into HKDF-SHA256 together with the
		    master salt to derive the session key used for all
		    normal cluster traffic.
		</para></listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	    Can be overridden per cluster using the
	    <varname>password=</varname> key in the
	    <varname>cluster</varname> parameter.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis>Default value is <quote>3eCrEt*5629</quote>.
	    Change this in production.</emphasis> Use a long, high-entropy
	    secret rather than a memorable phrase — scrypt raises the cost of
	    an offline guess, but only a strong secret removes the risk. A
	    generated key is ideal, e.g. <command>openssl rand -base64 32</command>.
	    The module logs a startup warning if the configured password is the
	    default or has an estimated entropy below 80 bits.
	</para>
	<example>
	    <title>Set <varname>password</varname> parameter</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("clusterer_controller", "password", "MyStr0ngPassw0rd!")
...
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	</section>

	<section id="param_manage_shtags" xreflabel="manage_shtags">
	<title><varname>manage_shtags</varname> (integer)</title>
	<para>
	    When set to <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis> (the default),
	    the controller master node automatically manages sharing tag
	    failover for all clusters. The controller becomes the single
	    decision point for which node holds the active tag, eliminating
	    races between nodes and requiring no script-level event routes
	    or MI commands to handle failover. While active, the
	    <function>clusterer_set_tag_active</function> MI command and
	    the <varname>$shtag()</varname> script variable setter are
	    blocked for controller-managed clusters, returning an error
	    to the caller.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Behaviour when <varname>manage_shtags=1</varname>:
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Startup:</emphasis> all local sharing tags
	    are forced to <emphasis>backup</emphasis> state during module
	    initialisation, regardless of the <emphasis>=active</emphasis>
	    value in the clusterer <varname>sharing_tag</varname> modparam.
	    The deferred BIN broadcast flag is also cleared so no
	    <emphasis>SHTAG_ACTIVE</emphasis> packet is ever sent at
	    startup. This ensures that no node can steal the active tag from
	    an existing cluster member simply by restarting.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Bootstrap:</emphasis> when the first node
	    starts alone and no existing master responds within
	    <varname>query_time</varname> seconds (join deadline), it elects
	    itself master and activates all local backup tags exactly once.
	    Nodes that join an existing cluster are never eligible for this
	    bootstrap path and never self-activate.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Failover:</emphasis> when any node departs
	    (graceful shutdown via GOODBYE packet, or timeout-based removal),
	    the controller master activates its own backup tags for that
	    cluster. This covers all departure scenarios: last node standing,
	    master still present, and post re-election.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Rejoin:</emphasis> a node rejoining an
	    existing cluster always starts in backup state and never reclaims
	    the active tag from the current holder, even if
	    <emphasis>=active</emphasis> appears in its config.
	</para>
	<para>
	    When set to <emphasis role="bold">0</emphasis>, the controller
	    does not touch sharing tag state at all. The
	    <emphasis>=active</emphasis> config value,
	    <varname>seed_fallback_interval</varname>, and external
	    MI/event-route scripts behave exactly as in stock clusterer
	    without the controller. Use this when you have existing tag
	    management scripts and want to opt out of automatic failover.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis>Default value is <quote>1</quote>.</emphasis>
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Global vs per-cluster scope:</emphasis>
	    This modparam sets a global default that applies to every cluster
	    defined via the <varname>cluster</varname> modparam. Individual
	    clusters can override it by including
	    <emphasis>manage_shtags=0</emphasis> or
	    <emphasis>manage_shtags=1</emphasis> directly in the cluster
	    string. The global default is resolved at startup after all
	    modparams are processed, so the order of
	    <varname>manage_shtags</varname> and <varname>cluster</varname>
	    lines in the config file does not matter.
	</para>
	<example>
	    <title>Global <varname>manage_shtags</varname> — applies to all clusters</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
...
# Enable automatic failover for every cluster (this is also the default)
modparam("clusterer_controller", "manage_shtags", 1)
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster", "id=1,multicast=239.0.90.1:3333")
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster", "id=2,multicast=239.0.90.2:3333")
...
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	<example>
	    <title>Per-cluster override — opt one cluster out of automatic failover</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
...
# manage_shtags=1 globally, but cluster 2 uses its own MI/event-route scripts
modparam("clusterer_controller", "manage_shtags", 1)
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster",
    "id=1,multicast=239.0.90.1:3333")
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster",
    "id=2,multicast=239.0.90.2:3333,manage_shtags=0")
...
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	<example>
	    <title>Global opt-out with one cluster opting in</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
...
# Disable automatic failover globally; enable it only for cluster 1
modparam("clusterer_controller", "manage_shtags", 0)
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster",
    "id=1,multicast=239.0.90.1:3333,manage_shtags=1")
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster",
    "id=2,multicast=239.0.90.2:3333")
...
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	<example>
	    <title>Typical full configuration with manage_shtags=1 (default)</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
# All nodes use identical config — only the BIN socket IP differs per node.
# The =active tag value in sharing_tag is ignored by the controller;
# it is kept in the config only for compatibility with manage_shtags=0.

socket=bin:10.22.23.191:3857

loadmodule "proto_bin.so"

loadmodule "clusterer.so"
modparam("clusterer", "use_controller", 1)
modparam("clusterer", "sharing_tag",   "vip1/1=active")
modparam("clusterer", "ping_interval", 4)
modparam("clusterer", "ping_timeout",  1500)

loadmodule "clusterer_controller.so"
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster",  "id=1,multicast=239.0.90.1:3333")
modparam("clusterer_controller", "password", "MyStr0ngPassw0rd!")
# manage_shtags defaults to 1 — no need to set it explicitly
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	</section>

	<section id="param_master_stickiness" xreflabel="master_stickiness">
	<title><varname>master_stickiness</varname> (integer)</title>
	<para>
	    Controls whether a live master keeps its role when a higher-IP
	    node joins. Default <emphasis>1</emphasis> (sticky).
	</para>
	<para>
	    The module recognises three roles per cluster:
	    <emphasis role="bold">master</emphasis> (the active coordinator),
	    <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> (the standby that takes
	    over when the master fails), and
	    <emphasis role="bold">member</emphasis> (all other nodes). The
	    backup is always the highest-IP node that is not the master.
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">master_stickiness=1</emphasis> (default):
		the master is <emphasis>sticky</emphasis> — a live master keeps
		the role and is not displaced when a higher-IP node joins. The
		newly joined node becomes the backup (replacing the previous
		backup if it has a higher IP); the master only changes when the
		current master actually fails, at which point the backup is
		promoted. This minimises the number of master handovers.
	    </para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis role="bold">master_stickiness=0</emphasis>: pure
		highest-IP election — a higher-IP node takes over as master as
		soon as it appears. This produces more handovers but always
		keeps the highest-IP node as master.
	    </para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>
	    In both modes a split-brain (two nodes each believing they are
	    master, e.g. after a network partition heals) is resolved
	    deterministically: the lower-IP master yields to the higher-IP one.
	</para>
	<para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Global vs per-cluster scope:</emphasis>
	    like <varname>manage_shtags</varname>, this sets a global default
	    that individual clusters can override with
	    <emphasis>master_stickiness=0</emphasis> or
	    <emphasis>master_stickiness=1</emphasis> in the
	    <varname>cluster</varname> string. Resolution happens at startup
	    regardless of modparam order.
	</para>
	<example>
	    <title>Set <varname>master_stickiness</varname> parameter</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
...
# Global default (sticky) — omit entirely for the same effect
modparam("clusterer_controller", "master_stickiness", 1)

# Per-cluster override: cluster 2 always promotes the highest-IP node
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster",
    "id=1,multicast=239.0.90.1:3333")
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster",
    "id=2,multicast=239.0.90.2:3333,master_stickiness=0")
...
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	</section>

	<section id="param_on_config_mismatch" xreflabel="on_config_mismatch">
	<title><varname>on_config_mismatch</varname> (string)</title>
	<para>
	    Policy applied when a node's consistency-critical settings
	    (<varname>manage_shtags</varname>,
	    <varname>master_stickiness</varname>, <varname>query_time</varname>)
	    differ from those of the running cluster. All nodes of a cluster are
	    expected to use identical values; this parameter decides what happens
	    when they do not. One of:
	    <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>reject</emphasis> (default) - the
		master refuses the join with a JOIN_REJECT and the joining node
		shuts down after logging which settings differ.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>warn</emphasis> - the node is allowed
		to join; a single <emphasis>CONFIG MISMATCH</emphasis> warning is
		logged per mismatching peer.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>adopt</emphasis> - the joining node
		adopts the running cluster's settings at runtime and
		continues.</para></listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	    Global only (not per-cluster). Default: <emphasis>reject</emphasis>.
	</para>
	<example>
	    <title>Set <varname>on_config_mismatch</varname> parameter</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("clusterer_controller", "on_config_mismatch", "reject")
...
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	</section>

    </section><!-- exported_parameters -->

    <section id="exported_mi" xreflabel="Exported MI Functions">
    <title>Exported MI Functions</title>

	<section id="mi_cc_list_members" xreflabel="cc_list_members">
	<title><function moreinfo="none">cc_list_members</function></title>
	<para>
	    List all current cluster members with their node_id, status and
	    BIN socket addresses. Status is one of <emphasis>master</emphasis>,
	    <emphasis>backup</emphasis> (the standby that will be promoted if
	    the master fails) or <emphasis>member</emphasis>. Only peers within
	    the current election window are shown.
	</para>
	<para>Parameters: <emphasis>none</emphasis></para>
	<example>
	    <title><function>cc_list_members</function> usage</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
opensips-cli -x mi cc_list_members
[
    {
        "cluster_id": 1,
        "members": [
            {
                "ip": "10.22.23.191",
                "node_id": 1,
                "status": "master",
                "bin_sockets": [ "bin:10.22.23.191:3857" ]
            },
            {
                "ip": "10.22.23.193",
                "node_id": 2,
                "status": "backup",
                "bin_sockets": [ "bin:10.22.23.193:3857" ]
            },
            {
                "ip": "10.22.23.192",
                "node_id": 3,
                "status": "member",
                "bin_sockets": [ "bin:10.22.23.192:3857" ]
            }
        ]
    }
]
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	</section>

	<section id="mi_cc_node_info" xreflabel="cc_node_info">
	<title><function moreinfo="none">cc_node_info</function></title>
	<para>
	    Return full information for a specific node identified by
	    its allocated node_id.
	</para>
	<para>Parameters:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para>
		<emphasis>node_id</emphasis> — the integer node_id to
		look up.
	    </para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<example>
	    <title><function>cc_node_info</function> usage</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
opensips-cli -x mi cc_node_info node_id=2
{
    "node_id": 2,
    "ip": "10.22.23.192",
    "cluster_id": 1,
    "status": "backup",
    "bin_sockets": [ "bin:10.22.23.192:3857" ]
}
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	</section>

	<section id="mi_cc_list_config" xreflabel="cc_list_config">
	<title><function moreinfo="none">cc_list_config</function></title>
	<para>
	    List all configured clusters and their resolved settings — the
	    effective values actually in use after global defaults and
	    per-cluster overrides have been applied. Useful for confirming that
	    a per-cluster <varname>master_stickiness</varname> or
	    <varname>manage_shtags</varname> override took effect. The cluster
	    password is never exposed.
	</para>
	<para>
	    The <varname>shtag_mode</varname> field reports the current
	    sharing-tag allocation policy: <emphasis>auto</emphasis> when the
	    active tag follows the master automatically, or
	    <emphasis>override:&lt;node_id&gt;</emphasis> when an operator has
	    pinned a fixed holder with <function>cc_shtag_force</function>.
	</para>
	<para>Parameters: <emphasis>none</emphasis></para>
	<example>
	    <title><function>cc_list_config</function> usage</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
opensips-cli -x mi cc_list_config
[
    {
        "cluster_id": 1,
        "multicast": "239.0.90.1:3333",
        "my_ip": "10.22.23.191",
        "bin_socket": "bin:10.22.23.191:3857",
        "query_time": 5,
        "master_stickiness": 1,
        "manage_shtags": 1,
        "shtag_mode": "auto",
        "member_count": 3
    }
]
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	</section>

	<section id="mi_cc_shtag_force" xreflabel="cc_shtag_force">
	<title><function moreinfo="none">cc_shtag_force</function></title>
	<para>
	    Force a specific node to hold the active sharing tag, overriding the
	    normal master-driven allocation. This is useful for planned
	    maintenance or manual traffic steering: the chosen node becomes the
	    sole active shtag holder cluster-wide while every other node —
	    including the master — is put into backup for that tag.
	</para>
	<para>
	    The command must be issued on the current <emphasis>master</emphasis>
	    (it returns an error otherwise). The override is propagated to all
	    members in the MEMBER_LIST and <emphasis>survives master
	    fail-over</emphasis>: a newly elected master keeps honouring it rather
	    than reclaiming the tag. Automatic allocation stays suspended until
	    <function>cc_shtag_auto</function> is called. If the forced node
	    leaves the cluster or times out, the override is cleared
	    automatically and automatic allocation resumes.
	</para>
	<para>Parameters:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>cluster_id</emphasis> — the target cluster.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>node_id</emphasis> — the node that must hold the active tag; it must be a current member of the cluster.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<example>
	    <title><function>cc_shtag_force</function> usage</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
opensips-cli -x mi cc_shtag_force cluster_id=1 node_id=3
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	</section>

	<section id="mi_cc_shtag_auto" xreflabel="cc_shtag_auto">
	<title><function moreinfo="none">cc_shtag_auto</function></title>
	<para>
	    Clear any override set by <function>cc_shtag_force</function> and
	    resume automatic, master-driven sharing-tag allocation — the active
	    tag follows the master again. Must be issued on the current master.
	</para>
	<para>Parameters:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>cluster_id</emphasis> — the target cluster.</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<example>
	    <title><function>cc_shtag_auto</function> usage</title>
	    <programlisting format="linespecific">
opensips-cli -x mi cc_shtag_auto cluster_id=1
	    </programlisting>
	</example>
	</section>

    </section><!-- exported_mi -->

    <section id="multiple_clusters" xreflabel="Multiple Clusters">
    <title>Multiple Clusters</title>
    <para>
	A single &osips; instance can participate in multiple clusters
	simultaneously by repeating the <varname>cluster</varname>
	modparam. Each cluster runs an independent worker process with
	its own multicast socket, peer table, master election, and
	node_id space.
    </para>
    <para>
	Clusters are distinguished by the combination of their multicast
	IP address and UDP port. Two useful topologies are possible:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Different ports, same multicast IP</emphasis>
	    — convenient when all clusters share the same L2 segment.
	    The port number alone separates traffic for each cluster.
	    Each cluster's <varname>password</varname> should also
	    differ to provide an additional encryption barrier.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Different multicast IPs</emphasis>
	    — useful when clusters span different network segments or
	    when multicast routing is scoped differently per cluster.
	</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
	When multiple clusters are defined and the node has more than
	one BIN socket, the <varname>bin_socket=</varname> key must be
	specified in each cluster string to indicate which BIN socket
	to advertise for that cluster. If only one BIN socket exists,
	it is used for all clusters automatically.
    </para>
    <para>
	Each cluster has its own independent clusterer
	<varname>cluster_id</varname>, allowing different &osips;
	subsystems to replicate on different clusters:
    </para>
    <example>
	<title>Multiple clusters — dialog on cluster 1, usrloc on cluster 2</title>
	<programlisting format="linespecific">
# Two BIN sockets, one per cluster
socket=bin:10.0.1.10:5566
socket=bin:10.0.2.10:5566

loadmodule "proto_bin.so"

loadmodule "clusterer.so"
modparam("clusterer", "use_controller", 1)

loadmodule "clusterer_controller.so"
# Cluster 1 — dialog replication group, LAN segment 10.0.1.0/24
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster",
    "id=1,multicast=239.0.90.1:3333,bin_socket=bin:10.0.1.10:5566")
# Cluster 2 — usrloc replication group, LAN segment 10.0.2.0/24
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster",
    "id=2,multicast=239.0.90.1:3334,bin_socket=bin:10.0.2.10:5566")

loadmodule "dialog.so"
modparam("dialog", "dialog_replication_cluster", 1)

loadmodule "usrloc.so"
modparam("usrloc", "cluster_id", 2)
	</programlisting>
    </example>
    <example>
	<title>Multiple clusters — same multicast IP, different ports</title>
	<programlisting format="linespecific">
socket=bin:10.22.23.191:3857

loadmodule "proto_bin.so"

loadmodule "clusterer.so"
modparam("clusterer", "use_controller", 1)

loadmodule "clusterer_controller.so"
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster",
    "id=1,multicast=239.0.90.1:3333,password=ClusterOneSecret")
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster",
    "id=2,multicast=239.0.90.1:3334,password=ClusterTwoSecret")

loadmodule "dialog.so"
modparam("dialog", "dialog_replication_cluster", 1)

loadmodule "dispatcher.so"
modparam("dispatcher", "cluster_id", 2)
	</programlisting>
    </example>
    </section>

    <section id="configuration" xreflabel="Configuration Example">
    <title>Configuration Example</title>
    <para>
	The following example shows a minimal two-module configuration
	for zero-config HA clustering with dialog replication. The
	<function>loadmodule</function> order does not matter — the
	dependency system enforces correct initialization order
	automatically.
    </para>
    <example>
	<title>Minimal HA cluster configuration</title>
	<programlisting format="linespecific">
# Each node needs an explicit BIN socket (no wildcard)
socket=bin:10.22.23.191:3857

loadmodule "proto_bin.so"

loadmodule "clusterer.so"
modparam("clusterer", "use_controller", 1)
modparam("clusterer", "sharing_tag",   "vip1/1=active")
modparam("clusterer", "ping_interval", 4)
modparam("clusterer", "ping_timeout",  1500)

loadmodule "clusterer_controller.so"
modparam("clusterer_controller", "cluster",
    "id=1,multicast=239.0.90.1:3333")
modparam("clusterer_controller", "password", "MyStr0ngPassw0rd!")

loadmodule "tm.so"
modparam("tm", "tm_replication_cluster", 1)

loadmodule "dialog.so"
modparam("dialog", "dialog_replication_cluster", 1)
modparam("dialog", "cluster_auto_sync", 1)

loadmodule "dispatcher.so"
modparam("dispatcher", "cluster_id",           1)
modparam("dispatcher", "cluster_probing_mode", "distributed")
	</programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>
	The same configuration file (with the node-specific
	<emphasis>socket=bin:IP:PORT</emphasis> line changed per node)
	is used on every node. No other per-node customization is
	required.
    </para>
    </section>

    <section id="limitations" xreflabel="Limitations">
    <title>Limitations</title>
    <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	    IPv4 only. IPv6 multicast is not currently supported.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    The module pre-allocates approximately 152 KB of shared
	    memory (<emphasis>-m</emphasis>) per cluster and 6 KB of
	    private memory (<emphasis>-M</emphasis>) per worker process
	    at startup. If either allocation fails, OpenSIPS will refuse
	    to start with an error in the log.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    Wildcard BIN sockets (<emphasis>bin:*:PORT</emphasis>) are
	    rejected at startup. An explicit IP address must be used in
	    the <emphasis>socket=</emphasis> line.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    Node IDs are not persistent across a full cluster restart
	    (all nodes down simultaneously). IDs are reallocated
	    starting from 1 when the cluster reforms. This has no
	    operational impact as long as at least one node remains up
	    during rolling restarts.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    The multicast network must support IP multicast routing
	    between all cluster nodes. Nodes on different L3 segments
	    require PIM or similar multicast routing.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">PIM-DM networks:</emphasis> PIM Dense
	    Mode periodically re-floods multicast traffic (prune state
	    typically expires every 3 minutes). On slow or congested
	    networks this brief re-flood/prune cycle could cause a gap
	    in MASTER_ALIVE delivery and trigger a spurious master
	    re-election. If this occurs, increase the effective timeout
	    by raising <varname>CC_MASTER_KA_MISSED</varname> in the
	    source from 3 to 5 or higher. PIM Sparse Mode (PIM-SM) or
	    networks with IGMP snooping do not have this issue.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">L2 overlay tunnels (Geneve, VXLAN,
	    GRE):</emphasis> if the overlay presents a flat L2 segment
	    with multicast support, the controller works transparently.
	    However, some VXLAN deployments disable multicast entirely
	    (no underlay multicast group, no BUM replication) — in that
	    case the controller will not function, as it has no unicast
	    fallback. Encapsulation overhead also adds latency and
	    jitter; on high-latency overlays consider raising
	    <varname>CC_MASTER_KA_MISSED</varname> to avoid spurious
	    re-elections.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">IPsec-protected links:</emphasis>
	    native IPsec multicast requires GDOI/GET VPN (RFC 6407),
	    which is rarely deployed. The recommended approach is to
	    run multicast inside an inner tunnel (GRE-over-IPsec,
	    Geneve-over-IPsec) that presents a multicast-capable
	    interface. Running the controller over such a setup results
	    in double encryption (application-layer AES-256-GCM plus
	    IPsec ESP), which is harmless but adds minor CPU overhead.
	    IPsec ESP tunnel mode also reduces the effective MTU by
	    approximately 50 bytes, which compounds the MEMBER_LIST
	    fragmentation issue described below.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">MEMBER_LIST fragmentation:</emphasis>
	    the MEMBER_LIST packet grows with cluster size and reaches
	    approximately 4395 bytes at the maximum of 256 nodes.  This
	    exceeds the 1472-byte UDP payload budget of a standard
	    1500-byte MTU Ethernet link and requires IP fragmentation:
	    <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>Standard Ethernet (1500 MTU): 3 fragments</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>IPsec ESP tunnel (~1400 MTU): 4 fragments</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>GRE-over-IPsec (~1350 MTU): 4–5 fragments</para></listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	    All other packet types (ALIVE, JOIN_REQ, KEY_GRANT, GOODBYE,
	    etc.) fit comfortably within a single datagram on any of
	    these links.  The DF bit is not set, so IP fragmentation
	    occurs transparently where the network allows it.  However,
	    firewalls or stateless middleboxes that silently drop
	    fragmented UDP will prevent new nodes from joining, since
	    MEMBER_LIST is required to complete the join sequence.
	    Verify that fragmented UDP is permitted on all paths between
	    cluster nodes, particularly over VPN tunnels and across
	    datacenter firewalls.
	</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="planned" xreflabel="Planned Features">
    <title>Planned Features</title>
    <para>
	The following features are planned for future releases:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Node maintenance mode</emphasis> — an MI
	    command (plus a matching command to leave it) to place any
	    cluster member into maintenance mode. Maintenance mode
	    <emphasis>blocks all cluster operations</emphasis> of that member:
	    it becomes fully inert while remaining visible as a member. It
	    must not act as master or win elections (if it is currently
	    master it demotes and hands over first); it takes no backup or
	    other operational role; it holds no sharing tags (any active tag
	    it holds is released and re-allocated to another eligible node);
	    and all of its normal cluster activity (elections, shtag
	    activation, sync-driven actions) is suspended until maintenance is
	    cleared. The member is reported with an explicit
	    <emphasis>maintenance</emphasis> state in
	    <function>cc_list_members</function>/<function>cc_list_config</function>.
	    This allows safe rolling maintenance without the node
	    participating in or disrupting the cluster.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Whether a maintenance node is also removed from the underlying
	    <emphasis>clusterer</emphasis> replication topology is controlled by
	    a new <varname>evict_on_maintenance</varname> modparam (default
	    <emphasis>1</emphasis>; global default with per-cluster override,
	    like <varname>manage_shtags</varname>). With
	    <varname>evict_on_maintenance=1</varname> the node is evicted from
	    clusterer so peers stop syncing to and pinging it (a clean drain;
	    re-joining and re-syncing on exit). With
	    <varname>evict_on_maintenance=0</varname> the node stays in the
	    clusterer topology and keeps replicating usrloc, dialog and other
	    state with the rest of the cluster while in maintenance — it only
	    loses its master/backup/shtag roles at the controller level, so it
	    stays warm and needs no re-sync when maintenance is cleared.
	</para>
	<para>
	    When maintenance mode lands, <function>cc_shtag_force</function>
	    will additionally reject forcing a tag onto a node that is in
	    maintenance, and entering maintenance while a node holds a forced
	    tag will clear the override and re-allocate the tag.
	</para>
	<para>
	    Maintenance state will also be exposed to the routing script and to
	    the event system, so it can be reacted to from configuration:
	    <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		    <function>cc_in_maintenance()</function> — script function
		    returning true when the local node is in maintenance (for use
		    in an <emphasis>if</emphasis> test, e.g. to reply 503 and
		    drain), with a
		    <function>cc_node_in_maintenance(cluster_id, node_id)</function>
		    variant for a specific peer.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		    <function>cc_is_evicted()</function> — script function
		    returning whether the local node is currently evicted from the
		    <emphasis>clusterer</emphasis> replication topology (true when
		    in maintenance with <varname>evict_on_maintenance=1</varname>;
		    false when it stays in the topology and keeps replicating),
		    with a
		    <function>cc_node_is_evicted(cluster_id, node_id)</function>
		    variant for a specific peer. This lets a script distinguish a
		    node that is drained out of clusterer from one that is in
		    maintenance but still warm and syncing.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		    <emphasis>E_MAINTENANCE_MODE_CHANGE</emphasis> — an event
		    (usable from an <function>event_route</function> or any event
		    subscriber transport) raised on each maintenance transition,
		    carrying the cluster_id, node_id, IP, new state, whether it is
		    the local node, and whether it was evicted. The transition is
		    distributed to the other cluster members over the
		    <emphasis>clusterer</emphasis> BIN protocol (the same channel
		    clusterer uses for replication), and each receiving member
		    raises the event locally so its
		    <function>event_route</function> can react (for example the
		    master re-allocating sharing tags, or a node adjusting
		    dispatcher weights to drain signalling). Consistent with how
		    clusterer works, a node that is evicted from the clusterer
		    topology (<varname>evict_on_maintenance=1</varname>) is outside
		    the BIN mesh and therefore does <emphasis>not</emphasis> receive
		    maintenance <emphasis>events</emphasis> for other nodes while it
		    is evicted — that is expected (an evicted node is inert and has
		    nothing to react to).
		</para>
		<para>
		    The queryable per-node state is separate from the event: each
		    node's maintenance and evicted flags are propagated over the
		    controller's own multicast control plane (which a maintenance
		    node stays on even when evicted from clusterer), so the
		    <function>cc_in_maintenance()</function> /
		    <function>cc_node_in_maintenance()</function> and
		    <function>cc_is_evicted()</function> /
		    <function>cc_node_is_evicted()</function> accessors keep working
		    on <emphasis>any</emphasis> node — including one evicted from
		    clusterer — both for the local node and for other peers. In
		    short: the actionable event is limited to non-evicted BIN
		    members, but the status lookups are available everywhere on the
		    controller multicast group.
		</para></listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Observability and script integration</emphasis>
	    — surface cluster state through OpenSIPS's standard interfaces rather
	    than logs alone:
	    <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>Statistics</emphasis> - module
		statistics (current role, member count, master changes, nodes
		joined/left, JOIN_REJECTs, decrypt failures, config mismatches,
		split-brain merges) exposed via
		<function>get_statistics</function> and monitoring
		exporters.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>Events</emphasis> - events raised on
		state transitions (became master, demoted, node joined/left,
		split-brain merged, config mismatch, authentication reject),
		consumable from an <function>event_route</function> or any event
		subscriber transport.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>Pseudo-variables</emphasis> -
		read-only script variables such as <emphasis>$cc_role</emphasis>,
		<emphasis>$cc_is_master</emphasis>,
		<emphasis>$cc_master_ip</emphasis>,
		<emphasis>$cc_member_count</emphasis> (with an optional cluster_id
		index) so the routing script can branch on cluster
		role.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><emphasis>Script functions</emphasis> - e.g.
		<function>cc_is_master()</function>, alongside the maintenance
		accessors above.</para></listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </section>

</chapter>
