<!-- Module User's Guide -->

<chapter>

	<title>&adminguide;</title>

	<section>
	<title>Overview</title>
	<para>
	The WebSocket protocol (<ulink url='http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6455'>RFC 6455</ulink>)
	 provides an end-to-end full-duplex communication channel between two web-based applications.
	This allows WebSocket enabled browsers to connect to a WebSocket server
	and exchange any type of data.
	<ulink url='http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7118'>RFC 7118</ulink>
	provides the specifications for transporting SIP messages over the WebSocket protocol.
	</para>
	<para>
	The <emphasis role='bold'>proto_ws</emphasis> module is transport module that provides
	communication over the WebSocket protocol. This module is fully compliant with the
	<ulink url='http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7118'>RFC 7118</ulink>, thus allowing browsers
	to act as SIP clients for the &osips; proxy.
	</para>
	<para>
	The current implementation acts both as WebSocket server and client, thus it can 
	accept connections from WebSocket clients and can also initiate connections to another
	WebSocket server. After the connection is established, messages can flow  in
	both directions.
	</para>
	<para>&osips; supports the following WebSocket operations:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	text and binary - can both send and receive WebSocket messages that contain text or binary body
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	close - messages used to safely close the WebSocket communication using a 2-messages handshake
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	ping - responds with pong messages. There is no mechanism to trigger ping messages.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	pong - sent when a ping message is received. &osips;, absorbes the pong messages received.
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<para>
		Once loaded, you will be able to define WebSocket listeners in your script. To
		add a listener, you have to add its IP, and optionally the listening port,
		<emphasis>after</emphasis> the <varname>mpath</varname> parameter, similar to this
		example:
	<para>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
mpath=/path/to/modules
...
listen=ws:127.0.0.1		# change with the listening IP
listen=ws:127.0.0.1:5060	# change with the listening IP and port
...
</programlisting>
	</para>
	</para>
	</section>

	<section>
	<title>Dependencies</title>
	<section>
		<title>&osips; Modules</title>
		<para>
		The following modules must be loaded before this module:
			<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis>None</emphasis>.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>External Libraries or Applications</title>
		<para>
		The following libraries or applications must be installed before
		running &osips; with this module loaded:
			<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis>None</emphasis>.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>
	</section>

	<section>
	<title>Exported Parameters</title>
	<section>
		<title><varname>ws_port</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
		The default port to be used for all WS related operation. Be careful
		as the default port impacts both the SIP listening part (if no port is
		defined in the WS listeners) and the SIP sending part (if the 
		destination WS URI has no explicit port).
		</para>
		<para>
		If you want to change only the listening port for WS, use the port
		option in the SIP listener defintion.
		</para>
		<para>
		<emphasis>
			Default value is 80.
		</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>ws_port</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("proto_ws", "ws_port", 8080)
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title><varname>ws_send_timeout</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
		Time in milliseconds after a WebSocket connection will be closed if it is
		not available for blocking writing in this interval (and &osips; wants
		to send something on it).
		</para>
		<para>
		<emphasis>
			Default value is 100 ms.
		</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>ws_send_timeout</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("proto_ws", "ws_send_timeout", 200)
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title><varname>ws_max_msg_chunks</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
			The maximum number of chunks in which a SIP message is expected to
			arrive via WebSocket. If a received packet is more fragmented than this,
			the connection is dropped (either the connection is very
			overloaded and this leads to high fragmentation - or we are the
			victim of an ongoing attack where the attacker is sending very
			fragmented traffic in order to decrease server performance).
		</para>
		<para>
		<emphasis>
			Default value is 4.
		</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>ws_max_msg_chunks</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("proto_ws", "ws_max_msg_chunks", 8)
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	</section>

</chapter>
