<!-- Module User's Guide -->

<chapter>

  <title>&adminguide;</title>

  <section id="overview" xreflabel="Overview">
  <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
      The presence_xcapdiff is an &osips; module that adds support for the
      "xcap-diff" event to presence and pua. At the moment, the module
      just registers the event but doesn't do any event-specific processing.
      The module will automatically determine if the presence and/or pua
      modules are present and if so it will register the xcap-diff event
      with them. This allows the module to automatically offer presence
      or pua related functionality simply based on the presence of the
      aforementioned modules in the &osips; configuration, without any
      need for manual configuration.
    </para>
    <para>
      Registering the event with pua, allows the XCAP server to publish
      the xcap-event when some modification of a document happens.
      Registering the event with presence allows clients to subscribe
      to the event.
    </para>
    <para>
      The module is intended to be used with the OpenXCAP server (www.openxcap.org),
      although it doesn't contain any OpenXCAP-specific code and should be usable
      with any XCAP server.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="dependencies" xreflabel="Dependencies">
  <title>Dependencies</title>
    <section>
    <title>&osips; Modules</title>
      <para>
        The following modules must be loaded before this module:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>presence</emphasis> module - to enable clients to
              subscribe to the xcap-diff event package.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>pua</emphasis> module - to be able to publish the
              xcap-diff event when some modification of a document happens.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>pua_mi</emphasis> module - to enable pua to publish
              the xcap-diff event using the MI interface. This is needed if
              this module is intended to be used in conjunction with OpenXCAP.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
    <title>External Libraries or Applications</title>
      <para>
        The following libraries or applications must be installed before
        running &osips; with this module loaded:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>None</emphasis>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

</chapter>

