<!-- Module User's Guide -->

<chapter id="sec-admin-guide">
	<title>&adminguide;</title>

	<section id="sec-overview">
	<title>Overview</title>
	<para>
		The <emphasis>mid_registrar</emphasis> is a mid-component of a SIP platform,
		designed to work between end users and the platform's main registration component.

		It opens up new possibilities for leveraging existing infrastructure in
		order to continue to grow (as subscribers and as registration traffic)
		while keeping an existing low-resources registrar server.
	</para>
	<para>
		Acting as a registration front-end to the main SIP registrar, the mid-registrar is able to:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				convert incoming high-rate registration traffic into a low-rate variant,
				towards the main registrar layer. With proper configuration, it can
				absorb over 90% of existing registration traffic while
				preserving the back-end's user location state, effectively reducing
				resource usage at the respective layer.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				stay synchronized with the main registrar (from a user
				location perspective), by properly
				accepting the contact states and expirations it decides.
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="sec-working-modes">
	<title>Working modes</title>
	<para>
		The mid_registrar may function in one of several modes:
	</para>

	<section id="sec-mirror-mode">
		<title>Contact mirroring (default)</title>
		<para>
		In "contact mirroring" mode, the mid-registrar will insert itself
		in the registration flow between end user and main registrar only as
		a simple proxy registrar, without any other contact processing. The
		incoming REGISTER requests will be proxied further to the main
		registrar; the registered contact will be stored in the mid-registrar
		only on 2xx replies, according to the information returned by the main registrar.
		</para>
		<para>
		A possible usage of this mode, for example, would be to clone
		registrations on a SIP front-end that extends the main platform with
		new services (like adding IM/messaging routing).
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="sec-device-throttling-mode">
		<title>Contact throttling</title>
		<para>
		In "contact throttling" mode, the mid-registrar can significantly
		reduce the registration rate on the main registrar side (between
		mid-registrar and main registrar), while coping with a high registration
		rate on the end-user side (between end-user and mid-registrar). This
		is useful in scenarios were the end-users are very dynamic and short-lived 
		(like on mobile devices), but the main registrar cannot cope with large traffic.
		</para>
		<para>
		Traffic conversion is done in a <emphasis>"per-device"</emphasis>
		manner, according to each unique SIP Contact header field value. It is achieved by
		increasing the "expires" parameter value of each contact, when relaying
		registrations to the main registrar.
		Once such a registration is completed, subsequent registrations for the same
		SIP Contact header field value will be continuously absorbed by the mid-registrar
		until, eventually, the lifetime of the remote registration will have decreased
		enough that a refresh (i.e. simply forwarding the next REGISTER request) is mandatory.
		</para>
		<para>
		A common occurence is for some SIP User Agents to lose their network connection
		(especially when dealing with mobile devices), hence they do not properly de-register
		from the mid-registrar. In this case, in order to avoid stale registrations on the
		main registrar (which contains SIP contacts with greatly extended lifetimes!),
		the mid-registrar will appropriately generate De-REGISTER requests and remove
		these contacts from the main registrar's location service as soon as it considers
		them to have expired.
		</para>
		<para>
		The main practical use for this mode is registration traffic conversion.
		By minimizing the strain of processing registrations on the main registrar,
		we allow it to dedicate more system resources to critical areas of the
		platform, such as advanced SIP calling features and/or media handling.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="sec-user-throttling-mode">
		<title>AOR throttling</title>
		<para>
		In "AOR throttling" mode, the mid-registrar helps with handling multiple
		registrations per user/AOR. This is done by aggregating all the end-user
		registered contacts from a single AOR under a single registration into
		the main registrar. This can dramatically reduce the incoming rate of
		registrations (to a single registration per AOR), but also helps in dealing
		with registrar servers which are not able to implement parallel forking/ringing.
		</para>
		<para>
		Traffic conversion is done in a <emphasis>"per-user"</emphasis>
		manner, according to each unique SIP AOR. It is achieved by
		providing a contact with a large "expires" parameter value,
		when relaying registrations to the main registrar.
		Once such a registration is completed, subsequent registrations to the same
		Address-of-record  will be continuously absorbed by the mid-registrar until,
		eventually, the lifetime of the remote registration will have decreased enough
		that a refresh (i.e. simply forwarding the next REGISTER request) is mandatory.
		</para>
		<para>
		A common occurence is for some SIP User Agents to lose their network connection
		(especially when dealing with mobile devices), hence they do not properly de-register
		from the mid-registrar. In this case, in order to avoid stale registrations on the
		main registrar (which contains SIP AORs with greatly extended lifetimes!),
		the mid-registrar will appropriately generate De-REGISTER requests and remove
		these contacts from the main registrar's location service as soon as it considers
		them to have expired.
		</para>
		<para>
			Of all three modes, "AOR throttling" potentially offers the best reduction in
			traffic on the way to the main registrar. By aggregating contacts, it also
			has the added benefit of reducing the number of contacts that the main registrar
			must handle.
		</para>
		<para>
			Regarding SIP request mangling in this mode, the module will always
			replace all Contact header field values with a single Contact header
			field value when proxying registrations to the main registrar, indicating
			that the AOR is local to the front-end, and its contacts can be found there.
		</para>
		<para>
		The main practical uses for this mode are registration traffic conversion
		towards the main registrar, as well as taking over its call forking
		duties. By minimizing the
		strain of processing registrations / forking calls on the main registrar,
		we allow it to dedicate more system resources to critical areas of the
		platform, such as advanced SIP calling features and/or media handling.
		</para>
	</section>
	</section>

	<section id="sec-insertion-modes">
	<title>Insertion modes</title>
	<para>
		A defining feature of the mid-registrar is that it must be easy to integrate,
		ideally a "plug-and-play" SIP component. It should not impose any
		"outbound-proxy" configurations on any of the platform's layers and
		automatically insert itself on the call flow of successful registrations.
	</para>
	<para>
		The script writer can choose between two
		SIP insertion mechanisms: either by having the module modify Contact
		headers when forwarding registrations, or instruct it to make use
		of a Path header (RFC 3327).
	</para>
	<section id="sec-insertion-by-contact">
		<title>Insertion by Contact (default)</title>
		<para>
			This insertion mode will mangle the Contact header field values
			of all forwarded registration requests, by replacing any
			original IP and port of a Contact URI with those of one of the
			mid-registrar's listening interfaces.
		</para>
		<para>
			The mid-registrar will also append a parameter to each Contact URI
			("rid" by default, can be changed through the
			<emphasis><xref linkend="modparam-contact-match-param"/></emphasis> module parameter)
			This URI parameter allows reply contacts to be matched with request
			ones. This same parameter will also be used when
			routing calls to the users. In this case, it will be taken from
			the INVITE's Request-URI.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="sec-insertion-by-path">
		<title>Insertion by Path</title>
		<para>
			Instructs the module to append a "Path" header field to each
			forwarded registration request. By recording itself between each
			user and the main registrar, the mid-registrar allows subsequent
			calls to be properly routed to the called party.
		</para>
	</section>
	</section>

	<section id="sec-dependencies">
	<title>Dependencies</title>
	<section id="sec-module-dependencies">
		<title>&osips; Modules</title>
		<para>
		The following modules must be loaded before this module:
			<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis>usrloc</emphasis>
			</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis>signaling</emphasis>
			</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis>tm</emphasis>
			</para>
			</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="sec-external-dependencies">
		<title>External Libraries or Applications</title>
		<para>
		The following libraries or applications must be installed before
		running &osips; with this module loaded:
			<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis>None</emphasis>
			</para>
			</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>
	</section>

	<section id="sec-modparam">
	<title>Exported Parameters</title>

	<section id="modparam-mode" xreflabel="mode">
		<title><varname>mode</varname> (integer)</title>

		<para>
			Working mode of the module.
			Refer to <xref linkend="sec-working-modes"/> for
			more details.
		</para>

		<para>
			The following is true for <emphasis role='bold'>all</emphasis> working modes:
			<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			when a REGISTER is received, the script writer must call
			<emphasis><xref linkend="modfunc-mid-registrar-save"/></emphasis>
			</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			the mid-registrar will insert itself on the call flow of
			all registrations according to the
			<emphasis><xref linkend="modparam-insertion-mode"/></emphasis>.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para>
			registrations handled by the mid-registrar will transparently
			result in a user location update if their reply status is 2xx.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>

		<para>
			Each working mode behaves differently, as follows:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<para>
			<emphasis>0 (Contact mirroring mode)</emphasis>
			<para>
			The module will only insert itself on the call flow.
			Contact expirations are left unchanged.
			</para>
		</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<para>
			<emphasis>1 (Contact throttling mode)</emphasis>
			<para>
			Contact throttling is a first step in lowering registration traffic rates. This
			is possible through the use of the
			<emphasis><xref linkend="modparam-outgoing-expires"/></emphasis> module
			parameter or the corresponding parameter to
			<emphasis><xref linkend="modfunc-mid-registrar-save"/></emphasis>,
			which allow the script writer to prolong the life of the registrations on the way
			to the main registrar.
			</para>

			<para>
			In this mode, the
			mid-registrar may alter Expires header field values or "expires" Contact
			header field parameters found in the initial request when forwarding registrations, according to
			<emphasis><xref linkend="modparam-outgoing-expires"/></emphasis>
			</para>
		</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<para>
			<emphasis>2 (AOR throttling mode)</emphasis>
		<para>
		AOR throttling is a step beyond "Contact throttling", as the main registrar
		is made aware of the network presence of AORs, rather than Contacts. This behaviour
		is also made possible through the
		<emphasis><xref linkend="modparam-outgoing-expires"/></emphasis> module
		parameter or the corresponding parameter to
		<emphasis><xref linkend="modfunc-mid-registrar-save"/></emphasis>,
		which allow the script writer to prolong the life of the registrations on the way
		to the main registrar.
		</para>
		<para>
		In this mode, the mid-registrar will fully replace the Contact
		set of all forwarded registrations with a single Contact, advertising
		that the AOR is available to the main registrar. The expiration value
		for this Contact is given by 
		<emphasis><xref linkend="modparam-outgoing-expires"/></emphasis>.
		</para>
		</para>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>


		<para>
			Default value is <emphasis role='bold'>0</emphasis> (contact mirroring mode)
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Setting the <emphasis>mode</emphasis> module parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
modparam("mid_registrar", "mode", 2)
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="modparam-insertion-mode" xreflabel="insertion_mode">
		<title><varname>insertion_mode</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
			SIP insertion mode of the module. Refer to
			<xref linkend="sec-insertion-modes"/> for more details. Possible
			values are:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<para>
			<emphasis>0 (Insertion by Contact)</emphasis>
		</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<para>
			<emphasis>1 (Insertion by Path)</emphasis>
		</para>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		Default value is <emphasis role='bold'>0</emphasis> (route by Contact)
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Setting the <emphasis>insertion_mode</emphasis> module parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
modparam("mid_registrar", "insertion_mode", 1)
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="modparam-outgoing-expires" xreflabel="outgoing_expires">
		<title><varname>outgoing_expires</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
			Only relevant in Contact/AOR throttling modes. Sets the default
			value for the expiration intervals of outgoing contacts. Values for
			this parameter which are shorter than the expiration intervals of
			some contacts present in a REGISTER request being processed will
			lead to the outgoing expiration intervals of these contacts
			remaining unchanged.
		</para>

		<para>
		Default value is <emphasis role='bold'>600</emphasis> (seconds)
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Setting the <emphasis>outgoing_expires</emphasis> module parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
modparam("mid_registrar", "outgoing_expires", 3600)
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="modparam-contact-match-param" xreflabel="contact_match_param">
		<title><varname>contact_match_param</varname> (string)</title>
		<para>
			Only relevant in "Contact throttling" mode. Specifies the name of the
			Contact URI parameter which is used by the module in order to
			match contacts and route calls.
		</para>

		<para>
			Default value is <emphasis role='bold'><quote>rid</quote></emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Setting the <emphasis>contact_match_param</emphasis> module parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
modparam("mid_registrar", "contact_match_param", "regid")
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="modparam-default-q" xreflabel="default_q">
		<title><varname>default_q</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
		Sets the default <emphasis>"q"</emphasis> value for new contacts.
		Because &osips; does not support floating point module parameters,
		the supplied <emphasis>"q"</emphasis> value must be multiplied by 1000.
		For example, if you want
		<emphasis><xref linkend="modparam-default-q"/></emphasis>
		to be 0.38, set this parameter to 380.
		</para>

		<para>
		Default value is <emphasis role='bold'>0</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Setting the <emphasis>default_q</emphasis> module parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
modparam("mid_registrar", "default_q", 380)
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="modparam-tcp-persistent-flag" xreflabel="tcp_persistent_flag">
		<title><varname>tcp_persistent_flag</varname> (string)</title>
		<para>
		Specifies the message flag to be used to control the
		module behaviour regarding TCP connections. If the flag is set for a
		REGISTER via TCP containing a TCP contact, the module, via the
		<emphasis><xref linkend="modfunc-mid-registrar-save"/></emphasis>
		function, will set the lifetime of the TCP
		connection to the contact expire value. By doing this, the TCP
		connection will stay up as long as its contacts are valid.
		</para>

		<para>
		Default value is <emphasis role='bold'>-1</emphasis> (not set)
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Setting the <emphasis>tcp_persistent_flag</emphasis> module parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
modparam("mid_registrar", "tcp_persistent_flag", "TCP_PERSIST_REGISTRATIONS")
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="modparam-realm-prefix" xreflabel="realm_prefix">
		<title><varname>realm_prefix</varname> (string)</title>
		<para>
		In multi-domain user location scenarios
		(<emphasis role='bold'>"use_domain"</emphasis> usrloc module parameter
		set to <emphasis>"1"</emphasis>),
		this parameter denotes a prefix to be automatically stripped from the
		hostname part of <emphasis>To</emphasis> header field URIs when doing
		a save, or <emphasis>Request-URIs</emphasis> when doing a lookup.
		</para>
		<para>
		It is meant as an alternative to DNS SRV records (not all SIP clients
		support SRV lookups), a subdomain of
		 the master domain can be defined for SIP purposes (like
		 "sip.mydomain.net" pointing to same IP address as the SRV record for
		 "mydomain.net"). By ignoring the realm_prefix "sip.", at registration,
		 "sip.mydomain.net" will be translated to "mydomain.net".
		</para>

		<para>
		Default value is <emphasis role='bold'>NULL</emphasis> (none)
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Setting the <emphasis>realm_prefix</emphasis> module parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
modparam("mid_registrar", "realm_prefix", "sip.")
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="modparam-case-sensitive" xreflabel="case_sensitive">
		<title><varname>case_sensitive</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
		If set to 1, then <acronym>AOR</acronym> comparison will be case
		sensitive (as RFC3261 instructs), if set to 0 then
		<acronym>AOR</acronym> comparison will be case insensitive.
		</para>
		<para>
		Default value is <emphasis role='bold'>1</emphasis> (true)
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Setting the <emphasis>case_sensitive</emphasis> module parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
modparam("mid_registrar", "case_sensitive", 0)
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="modparam-received-avp" xreflabel="received_avp">
		<title><varname>received_avp</varname> (string)</title>
		<para>
		The module will store the value of the AVP configured by this
		parameter in the <emphasis>received</emphasis> column of the user
		location table. It will leave the column empty if the AVP is empty.
		The AVP should contain a SIP URI consisting of the source IP, port,
		and protocol of the REGISTER message being processed.
		</para>
		<note>
		<para>
			The value of this parameter should be the same as the value of
			corresponding parameter of nathelper module.
		</para>
		</note>
		<para>
		Default value is <emphasis role='bold'>"NULL"</emphasis> (disabled)
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Setting the <emphasis>received_avp</emphasis> module parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
modparam("mid_registrar", "received_avp", "$avp(rcv)")
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="modparam-received-param" xreflabel="received_param">
		<title><varname>received_param</varname> (string)</title>
		<para>
		The name of the parameter that will be appended to Contacts of
		200 OK replies if the received URI is set by nathelper module.
		</para>
		<note>
		<para>
			The value of this parameter should be the same as the value of
			corresponding parameter of nathelper module.
		</para>
		</note>
		<para>
		Default value is <emphasis role='bold'>"received"</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Setting the <emphasis>received_param</emphasis> module parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
modparam("mid_registrar", "received_param", "rcv")
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="modparam-max-contacts" xreflabel="max_contacts">
		<title><varname>max_contacts</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
		This parameter can be used to limit the number of contacts per
		AOR (Address-of-Record) allowed at mid-registrar level. A value of
		<emphasis role='bold'>0</emphasis> disables the check.
		</para>
		<para>
		This is a global value and will only be used if no other value
		(for max_contacts) is passed as parameter to
		<emphasis><xref linkend="modfunc-mid-registrar-save"/></emphasis>
		(i.e. a "max_contacts" function flag will override this parameter)
		</para>
		<para>
			Default value is <emphasis role='bold'>0</emphasis> (disabled)
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Setting the <emphasis>max_contacts</emphasis> module parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
modparam("mid_registrar", "max_contacts", 10)
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="modparam-retry-after" xreflabel="retry_after">
		<title><varname>retry_after</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
		The mid-registrar can generate 5xx replies to registrations in various
		situations. It could, for example, happen when the
		<emphasis><xref linkend="modparam-max-contacts"/></emphasis> parameter
		is set and the processing of REGISTER request would exceed the limit.
		In this case, OpenSIPS would respond with "503 Service Unavailable".
		</para>
		<para>
		If you want to add the Retry-After header field in 5xx replies, set
		this parameter to a value greater than zero (0 means: do not add the
		header field). See section 20.33 of RFC3261 for more details.
		</para>
		<para>
		Default value is <emphasis role='bold'>0</emphasis> (disabled)
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Setting the <emphasis>retry_after</emphasis> module parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
modparam("mid_registrar", "retry_after", 30)
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="modparam-disable-gruu" xreflabel="disable_gruu">
		<title><varname>disable_gruu</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
			Globally disable GRUU handling.
		</para>
		<para>
		Default value is <emphasis role='bold'>1</emphasis> (GRUUs will not be handled)
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Setting the <emphasis>gruu_secret</emphasis> module parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
modparam("mid_registrar", "disable_gruu", 0)
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	<section id="modparam-gruu-secret" xreflabel="gruu_secret">
		<title><varname>gruu_secret</varname> (string)</title>
		<para>
		The string that will be used in XORing when generating
		temporary GRUUs.
		</para>
		<para>
		Default value is <emphasis role='bold'>"0p3nS1pS"</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Setting the <emphasis>gruu_secret</emphasis> module parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
modparam("mid_registrar", "gruu_secret", "my_secret")
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	</section>

	<section id="sec-modfunc">
	<title>Exported Functions</title>
	<section id="modfunc-mid-registrar-save" xreflabel="mid_registrar_save()">
		<title>
		<function moreinfo="none">mid_registrar_save(domain[, [flags][, [aor][, [outgoing_expires]]]])</function>
		</title>
		<para>
		Function to be called when handling REGISTER requests. This function
		decides if a REGISTER should be forwarded to the main registrar and
		performs all the necessary changes over the registered contacts. The
		function is also covering the handling of the 2xx REGISTER replies -
		the contacts confirmed by the main registrar will be automatically
		saved in the local user location (without any additional scripting).
		</para>
		<para>
			In Contact/AOR throttling modes (more info about working modes in <xref linkend="sec-working-modes"/>),
			the return value of this function indicates whether the script
			writer must forward the REGISTER request to the main registrar,
			or just wrap up any left-over processing and exit script execution, as
			the current REGISTER request has been answered with 200 OK
			(absorbed at mid-registrar level).
		</para>
		<para>
			Depending on the current working
			<emphasis><xref linkend="modparam-mode"/></emphasis> and
			<emphasis><xref linkend="modparam-insertion-mode"/></emphasis>,
			the function may additionally perform
			the following series of transformations when relaying REGISTER requests:
		</para>
		<para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para> in <emphasis>"Contact throttling"</emphasis> mode </para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								change the value of the <emphasis>Expires</emphasis>
								header field to the value of
								<emphasis>outgoing_expires</emphasis>, if given,
								otherwise the value given by the
								<emphasis><xref linkend="modparam-outgoing-expires"/></emphasis>
								module parameter.
								The same applies to any <emphasis>";expires"</emphasis>
								Contact URI parameter.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								replace the "host:port" part of all Contact URIs of the
								incoming REGISTER request with an OpenSIPS listening interface
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								append a parameter to each
								<emphasis>Contact</emphasis> URI, which will
								allow the module to match the reply contacts
								and also route calls. The name of this URI
								parameter is configurable via
								<emphasis><xref linkend="modparam-contact-match-param"/></emphasis>
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								append a "Path" header to the current REGISTER request
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para> in <emphasis>"AOR throttling"</emphasis> mode </para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								change the value of the <emphasis>Expires</emphasis>
								header field to the value of
								<emphasis>outgoing_expires</emphasis>, if given,
								otherwise the value given by the
								<emphasis><xref linkend="modparam-outgoing-expires"/></emphasis>
								module parameter.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								replace all <emphasis>Contact</emphasis> header
								fields of the request with a single <emphasis>Contact</emphasis> header field,
								which will contain the following SIP URI: "sip:address-of-record@proxy_ip:proxy_port"
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								append a "Path" header to the current REGISTER request
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>

		<para>Meaning of the parameters is as follows:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis>domain</emphasis> - logical domain within the registrar.
			If a database is used, then this must be name of the <emphasis>usrloc</emphasis>
			table which stores the contacts
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			<emphasis>flags</emphasis> (optional) - string of
			the following flags:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis>'m' (Memory only)</emphasis> - save the
					contacts only in memory cache without no DB operation;
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis>'r' (no Reply)</emphasis> - do not
					generate a SIP reply to the current REGISTER request.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<!--
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis>'cnn' (max Contacts)</emphasis> -  this
					flag can be used to limit the number of contacts for this
					AOR (Address of Record) in the user location database.
					Value 0 disables the check. This parameter overrides the
					global "max_contacts" module parameter.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis>'e(int)' (minimum expires)</emphasis> -  this
					flag can be used to set minimum register expiration time.
					Values lower than this minimum will be automatically set
					to the minimum. Value 0 disables the checking.
					This parameter overrides the global "min_expires" module parameter.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				!-->
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis>'p0' (Path support - 'off' mode)</emphasis>
					The Path header is saved into usrloc, but is never
					included in the reply.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis>'p1' (Path support - lazy mode)</emphasis>
					The Path header is saved into usrloc, but is only included
					in the reply if path support is indicated in the
					registration request by the <quote>path</quote> option
					of the <quote>Supported</quote> header.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis>'p2' (Path support - strict mode)</emphasis>
					The path header is only saved into usrloc, if path support
					is indicated in the registration request by the
					<quote>path</quote> option of the <quote>Supported</quote>
					header. If no path support is indicated, the request is
					rejected with <quote>420 - Bad Extension</quote> and the
					header <quote>Unsupported: path</quote> is included in
					the reply along with the received <quote>Path</quote>
					header. This mode is the one recommended by RFC-3327.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis>'v' (path receiVed)</emphasis> if set,
					the <quote>received</quote> parameter of the first Path
					URI of a registration is set as received-uri and the NAT
					branch flag is set for this contact. This is useful if
					the registrar is placed behind a SIP loadbalancer, which
					passes the nat'ed UAC address as <quote>received</quote>
					parameter in it's Path uri.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>This parameter is a string composed of a set of flags.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis>aor (optional)</emphasis> - variable holding a custom Address-of-Record.
				If not given, the AOR will be taken from the <emphasis>To</emphasis> header URI
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis>outgoing_expires (optional, only relevant
			in Contact/AOR throttling modes)</emphasis> - custom value
		for the contact expiration interval of the outgoing REGISTER
		request, which overrides the default
			<emphasis><xref linkend="modparam-outgoing-expires"/></emphasis> module parameter.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para><emphasis role='bold'>Return value</emphasis></para>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				1 (success) - current REGISTER request must be dispatched by the
				script writer over to the main registrar
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				2 (success) - current REGISTER request has been absorbed by the
				mid-registrar; a 200 OK reply has been sent upstream
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				-1 (error) - generic error code; the logs should provide more help
			</para>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
		This function can only be used from the request route.
		</para>
		<example>
			<title><function moreinfo="none"><emphasis>mid_registrar_save</emphasis></function> usage</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
if (is_method("REGISTER")) {
	mid_registrar_save("location");
	switch ($retcode) {
	case 1:
		xlog("L_INFO", "forwarding REGISTER to main registrar...\n");
		$ru = "sip:10.0.0.3:5070";
		if (!t_relay()) {
			send_reply("500", "Server Internal Error 1");
		}

		break;
	case 2:
		xlog("L_INFO", "REGISTER has been absorbed!\n");
		break;
	default:
		xlog("L_ERR", "mid-registrar error!\n");
		send_reply("500", "Server Internal Error 2");
	}

	exit;
}
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	<section id="modfunc-mid-registrar-lookup" xreflabel="mid_registrar_lookup()">
		<title>
		<function moreinfo="none">mid_registrar_lookup(domain[, [flags][, [aor]]])</function>
		</title>
		<para>
		Function to be called when receiving requests from the main registrar
		(to be routed to the end-user). It performs the local lookup
		(in user location) and the necessary RURI processing in order to route
		the requests further to the end-user registered contacts (note that
		multiple branches/destinations may result after the lookup).
		</para>
		<para>
		Depending on the current working
		<emphasis><xref linkend="modparam-mode"/></emphasis>,
		the function will behave as follows:
		</para>

		<para>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<para> in <emphasis>"mirror"</emphasis> mode </para>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				extract the username (Address-of-Record) from the Request-URI
				and look up all of its contact bindings stored in the user
				location. The Request-URI (<emphasis role='bold'>$ru</emphasis>
				variable) will be overwritten with the highest q-value contact,
				with additional branches for each contact being optionally
				created. (depending on the <emphasis>flags</emphasis> parameter)
			</para>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<para> in <emphasis>"Contact throttling"</emphasis> mode </para>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				extract the <emphasis><xref linkend="modparam-contact-match-param"/></emphasis>
				from the Request-URI, derive the actual SIP URI of the destination
				from it and set it as the new Request-URI of the INVITE
				(<emphasis role='bold'>$ru</emphasis> variable).
			</para>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<para> in <emphasis>"AOR throttling"</emphasis> mode </para>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				extract the username (Address-of-Record) from the Request-URI
				and look up all of its contact bindings stored in the user
				location. The Request-URI (<emphasis role='bold'>$ru</emphasis>
				variable) will be overwritten with the highest q-value contact,
				with additional branches for each contact being optionally
				created. (depending on the <emphasis>flags</emphasis> parameter)
			</para>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</para>

		<para>Meaning of the parameters is as follows:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis>domain</emphasis> - logical domain within the registrar.
			If a database is used, then this must be name of the <emphasis>usrloc</emphasis>
			table which stores the contacts
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis>flags</emphasis>(optional)</para>
			<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				<emphasis>'b' (no Branches)</emphasis> - this flag controls how
				this function processes multiple contacts.  If there are
				multiple contacts for the given username in usrloc and this
				flag is not set, Request-URI will be overwritten with the
				highest-q rated contact and the rest will be appended to
				sip_msg structure and can be later used by tm for forking. If
				the flag is set, only Request-URI will be overwritten
				with the highest-q rated contact and the rest will be left
				unprocessed.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				<emphasis>'r' (bRanch lookup)</emphasis> - this flag enables
				searching through existing branches for aor's and expanding
				them to contacts. For example, you have got AOR A in your
				ruri but you also want to forward your calls to AOR B. In order
				to do this, you must put AOR B in a branch, and if this flag
				enabled, the function will also expand AOR B to contacts,
				which will be put back into the branches. The AOR's that were
				in branches before the function call shall be removed.
				</para>

				<para>
				<emphasis role='bold'>WARNING: </emphasis>
				<emphasis>if you want this flag activated,
				the 'b' (no Branches) flag must not be set, otherwise
				the lookup function will be unable to add new branches
				</emphasis>
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				<emphasis>'m' (Method filtering)</emphasis> - this flag tells
				if the contact filtering based on supported methods should be
				performed during lookup.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				<emphasis>'u' (User-Agent filtering)</emphasis> - this flag
				enables regexp filtering by user-agent. It's useful with
				enabled append_branches parameter. Regexp must follow
				the 'u' flag and must use format like 'u/regexp/'.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				<emphasis>'i' (Case insensitive search)</emphasis> - this flag
				enables case insensitive filtering for the 'u' flag.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				<emphasis>'e' (Use extended regexp)</emphasis> - this flag
				enables using of extended regexp format for the 'u' flag.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis>aor (optional)</emphasis> - variable holding a custom Address-of-Record.
				If not given, the AOR will be taken from the <emphasis>Request-URI</emphasis>
			</para>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para><emphasis role='bold'>Return value</emphasis></para>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				1 (success) - branch set successfully built
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				-1 (error) - generic error code; the logs should provide more help
			</para>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
		This function can only be used from the request route.
		</para>
		<example>
			<title><function moreinfo="none"><emphasis>mid_registrar_lookup</emphasis></function> usage</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
	# initial invites from the main registrar - need to look them up!
	if (is_method("INVITE") and $si == "10.0.0.3" and $sp == 5070) {
		if (!mid_registrar_lookup("location")) {
			t_reply("404", "Not Found");
			exit;
		}

		if (!t_relay())
			send_reply("500", "Server Internal Error 3");

	    exit;
	}
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>


	</section>
</chapter>

