<!-- Module User's Guide -->

<chapter>
	
	<title>&adminguide;</title>
	
	<section>
	<title>Overview</title>
	<para>
	The Call Center module implements an inbound call center system with call 
	flows (for queuing the received calls) and agents (for answering the 
	calls).
	</para>
	<para>
	The module implements the queuing system, the call distribution 
	to agents, agents managements, CDRs for the calls, statistics on 
	call distribution and agent's activity - basically everything 
	except the media playback (for the queue). This part must be provided via 
	a third party media server (FreeSwitch, Asterisk or others).
	</para>
	</section>

	<section>
	<title>How it works</title>
	<para>
	The main entities in the modules are the flows (queues) and agents.
	</para>
		<section>
		<title>DB tables</title>
		<para>
		Each entity has a corresponding table in the database, for 
		provisioning purposes - the <emphasis>cc_flows</emphasis> and 
		<emphasis>cc_agents</emphasis> tables, see
		<ulink url='http://www.opensips.org/Documentation/Install-DBSchema-1-11#AEN2361'>DB schema</ulink>.
		Data is loaded at startup and cached into memory ; runtime reload is 
		possible via the MI commands (see the <emphasis>cc_reload</emphasis> 
		command in <xref linkend="cc_mi_commands"/>).
		</para>
		<para>
		Additionally there is a table <emphasis>cc_cdrs</emphasis> for writing 
		the CDRs - this operation is done in realtime, after the call in 
		completed, covering all possible cases: call was dropped while in 
		queue, call was rejected by agent, call was accepted by agent, call 
		terminated with error - NOTE that a call may generate more than one 
		CDR (like call rejected by agent A, and redistributed and accepted by 
		agent B).
		</para>
		<para>
		The <emphasis>cc_calls</emphasis> table is used to store ongoing calls,
		regardless it's state (in queue, to the agent, ended). It is populated
		at runtime by the module and queried at startup. This table should not
		be manually provisioned.
		</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>Call Flows</title>
		<para>
		A flow is defined by a unique alphanumerical ID - the main attribute 
		of a flow is the <emphasis>skill</emphasis> - the skill is a 
		capability required by the flow for an agent to be able to answer the 
		call ; the concept of <emphasis>skills</emphasis> is the link between 
		the flows and the agents - telling what agents are serving what flows 
		- the flows require a skill, while the agents provide a set of skills. 
		Agents matching the required skill of a flow will automatically 
		receive calls from that flow.
		</para>
		<para>
		Additional, the flow has a <emphasis>priority</emphasis> - as agents 
		may server multiple flows in the same time (based on skills), you can
		define priorities between the flows - if the flows has a higher 
		priority, its calls will be pushed (in deliver to agents and queuing) in
		front of the calls from flows with a lower priority.
		</para>
		<para>
		Optionally, the flow may define a <emphasis>prependcid</emphasis> - a
		prefix to be added to the CLI (Caller ID) when the call is delivered to
		the agents - as an agent may receive call from multiple flows, it is 
		important for the user to see which was the queue a call was received.
		</para>
		<para>
		In terms of media announcements, the flow defines the 
		<emphasis>message_welcome</emphasis> (optional, to be played in the 
		call, before doing anything with the call) and 
		<emphasis>message_queue</emphasis> (mandatory, the looping message
		providing infinite on hold media IMPORTANT - this message must cycle 
		and media server must never hung up on it. Both announcements are 
		provided as SIP URIs (where the call has to be sent in order to get
		the playback).
		</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>Agents</title>
		<para>
		An agent is defined by a unique alphanumerical ID - the main attribute 
		of an agent is its the set of <emphasis>skills</emphasis> and its SIP
		<emphasis>location</emphasis>. The set of skills will tell what calls
		to be received (from which flows, based on the skill matching); the 
		location is a SIP URI where to call must be sent in order to be 
		answered by the agent.
		</para>
		<para>
		Additionally, the agent has a initial <emphasis>logstate</emphasis> - 
		if he is logged in or not (being logged in is a must in order to
		receive calls). The log state may be changed at runtime via a 
		dedicated MI command <emphasis>cc_agent_login</emphasis>, see 
		<xref linkend="cc_mi_commands"/>.
		</para>
		<para>
		There is a <emphasis>wrapup_time</emphasis> defined, saying the 
		time interval for an agent before getting a new call from the system 
		(after he finished a call).
		</para>
		</section>

	</section>


	<section>
	<title>Dependencies</title>
	<section>
		<title>&osips; Modules</title>
		<para>
		The following modules must be loaded before this module:
			<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis>b2b_logic</emphasis> - B2bUA module
			</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis>database</emphasis> - one of the SQL DB modules
			</para>
			</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>


	<section>
		<title>External Libraries or Applications</title>
		<para>
		The following libraries or applications must be installed before 
		running &osips; with this module loaded:
			<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>
				<emphasis>None</emphasis>.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>
	</section>


	<section>
	<title>Exported Parameters</title>

	<section>
		<title><varname>db_url</varname> (string)</title>
		<para>
		SQL address to the DB server -- database specific. This must be
		the Database holding the provisioning tables (cc_flows, cc_agents
		and cc_calls tables).
		</para>
		If not explicitly set, the global OpenSIPS DB URL will be used.
		<para>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>db_url</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("call_center", "db_url", 
	"mysql://opensips:opensipsrw@localhost/opensips")
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title><varname>acc_db_url</varname> (string)</title>
		<para>
		SQL address to the DB server -- database specific. This must be
		the Database where the CDRs table (cc_cdrs) is located.
		</para>
		If not explicitly set, the global OpenSIPS DB URL will be used.
		<para>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>acc_db_url</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("call_center", "acc_db_url", 
	"mysql://opensips:opensipsrw@localhost/opensips_cdrs")
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title><varname>b2b_scenario</varname> (string)</title>
		<para>
		The name of the B2B scenario that is used by the module for handling
		the calls in the queue. This is an advanced options and you should
		not change it unless you really understand what you are doing.
		</para>
		<para>
		The module provides an B2B scenario file 
		<emphasis>scenario_callcenter.xml</emphasis> located in the module
		directory. The name of this scenario from this file (which must be
		loaded via the b2b_logic module) must match the 
		<emphasis>b2b_scenario</emphasis> parameter.
		</para>
		<para>
		<emphasis>Default value is <quote>call center</quote>.
		</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>b2b_scenario</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("b2b_logic", "script_scenario", "/etc/opensips/scenario_callcenter.xml")
modparam("call_center", "b2b_scenario", "call center")
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title><varname>wrapup_time</varname> (integer)</title>
		<para>
		Time for an agent between finishing a call and receiving the next
		call from the system. Even if there are queued calls, the module
		will not deliver call to agent during this wrapup interval.
		</para>
		<para>
		<emphasis>Default value is <quote>30 seconds</quote>.
		</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>wrapup_time</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("call_center", "wrapup_time", 45)
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title><varname>queue_pos_param</varname> (string)</title>
		<para>
		The name of an SIP URI parameter to be used to report the position
		in the waiting queue when sending the call to media server for
		onwait/queue playback. The position 0 means it is the next call
		to be delivered to an agent.
		</para>
		<para>
		<emphasis>Default value is <quote>empty(none)</quote>.
		</emphasis>
		</para>
		<example>
		<title>Set <varname>queue_pos_param</varname> parameter</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
modparam("call_center", "queue_pos_param", "cc_pos")
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

</section>


	<section>
	<title>Exported Functions</title>
	<section>
		<title>
		<function>cc_handle_call(flowID)</function>
		</title>
		<para>
		This must be used only for initial INVITE requests - the function
		pushes the call to be handled by the call center module (via a certain
		flow/queue).
		</para>
		<para>
		This function can be used from REQUEST_ROUTE.
		</para>
		<para>
		The <emphasis role='bold'>flowID</emphasis> mandatory parameter is
		the ID of the flow to handle this call (push the call to that flow).
		This can be a variable or a static string.
		</para>
		<para>
		The function returns TRUE back to the script if the call was 
		successfully pushed and handled by the Call Center engine. IMPORTANT: 
		you must not do any signaling on the call (reply, relay) after this
		point.
		</para>
		<para>
		In case of error, FALSE is returned to the script with the following 
		return codes:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>
			<emphasis role='bold'>-1</emphasis> - unable to get the flow ID
			from the parameter;
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
			<emphasis role='bold'>-2</emphasis> - unable to parse the FROM URI;
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
			<emphasis role='bold'>-3</emphasis> - flow with FlowID not found;
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
			<emphasis role='bold'>-4</emphasis> - no agents logged in the flow;
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
			<emphasis role='bold'>-5</emphasis> - internal error;
			</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<example>
		<title><function>cc_handle_call</function> usage</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
if (is_method("INVITE") and !has_totag()) {
	if (!cc_handle_call("tech_support")) {
		send_reply("403","Cannot handle call");
		exit;
	}
}
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>
		<function>cc_agent_login(agentID, state)</function>
		</title>
		<para>
		This function sets the login (on or off) state for an agent.
		</para>
		<para>
		This function can be used from REQUEST_ROUTE.
		</para>
		<para>
		The <emphasis role='bold'>agentID</emphasis> mandatory parameter is
		the ID of the agent and the <emphasis role='bold'>state</emphasis>
		is an integer value giving the new state - 0 means logged off, 
		anything else means logged in.
		</para>
		<example>
		<title><function>cc_agent_login</function> usage</title>
		<programlisting format="linespecific">
...
# log off the 'agentX' agent
cc_agent_login("agentX","0");
...
</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>

	</section>


	<section>
	<title>Exported Statistics</title>

	<section>
	<title>Global statistics</title>
		<section>
		<title>ccg_incalls</title>
			<para>
			Total number of received calls. (counter type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>ccg_awt</title>
			<para>
			Global avg. waiting time for calls. (realtime type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>ccg_load</title>
			<para>
			Global load (across all flows). (realtime type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>ccg_distributed_incalls</title>
			<para>
			Total number of distributed calls. (counter type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>ccg_answered_incalls</title>
			<para>
			Total number of calls answered by agents. (counter type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>ccg_abandonned_incalls</title>
			<para>
			Total number of calls terminated by caller before being
			answered by agents. (counter type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>ccg_onhold_calls</title>
			<para>
			Total number of calls in the queues (onhold). (realtime type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>ccg_free_agents</title>
			<para>
			Total number of free agents (across all flows). (realtime type)
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
	<title>Per-flow statistics (one set for each flow)</title>
		<section>
		<title>ccf_incalls_flowID</title>
			<para>
			Number of received calls for the flow. (counter type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>ccf_dist_incalls_flowID</title>
			<para>
			Number of distributed calls in this flow. (counter type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>ccf_answ_incalls_flowID</title>
			<para>
			Nnumber of calls from the flow answered by agents. (counter type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>ccf_aban_incalls_flowID</title>
			<para>
			Number of calls (from the flow) terminated by caller before being
			answered by agents. (counter type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>ccf_onhold_incalls_flowID</title>
			<para>
			Number of calls (from the flow) which were put onhold.
			 (counter type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>ccf_queued_calls_flowID</title>
			<para>
			Number of calls which are queued for this flow. (realtime type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>ccf_free_agents_flowID</title>
			<para>
			Number of free agents serving this flow. (realtime type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>ccf_etw_flowID</title>
			<para>
			Estimated Time to Wait for this flow. (realtime type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>ccf_awt_flowID</title>
			<para>
			Avg. Wating Time for this flow. (realtime type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>ccg_load_flowID</title>
			<para>
			The load on the flow (number of queued calls versus number of
			logged agents). (realtime type)
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
	<title>Per-agent statistics (one set for each agent)</title>
		<section>
		<title>cca_dist_incalls_agnetID</title>
			<para>
			Number of distributed calls to this agent. (counter type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>cca_answ_incalls_agentID</title>
			<para>
			Nnumber of calls answered by the agent. (counter type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>cca_aban_incalls_agentID</title>
			<para>
			Number of calls (sent to this agent) terminated by caller before 
			being answered by agents. (counter type)
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>cca_att_agentID</title>
			<para>
			Avg. Talk Time for this agent (realtime type)
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	</section>


	<section id="cc_mi_commands">
	<title>Exported MI Functions</title>

	<section>
		<title>
		<function moreinfo="none">cc_reload</function>
		</title>
		<para>
		Command to reload flows and agents definition from database.
		</para>
		<para>
			It takes no parameter.
		</para>
		<para>
		MI FIFO Command usage:
		</para>
		<programlisting  format="linespecific">
opensipsctl fifo cc_reload
</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>
		<function moreinfo="none">cc_agent_login</function>
		</title>
		<para>
		Command to login an agent into the Call Center engine.
		</para>
		<para>
		It takes two mandatory parameters, the ID of the agent and the 
		new login state (0 - log off, 1 - log in)
		</para>
		<para>
		MI FIFO Command usage:
		</para>
		<programlisting  format="linespecific">
opensipsctl fifo cc_agent_login agentX 0
</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>
		<function moreinfo="none">cc_list_queue</function>
		</title>
		<para>
		Command to list all the calls in queuing - for each call, the 
		following attributes will be printed: the flow of the call, for how
		long the call is in the queue, the ETW for the call, call priority 
		and the call skill (inherited from the flow).
		</para>
		<para>
		It takes no parameter.
		</para>
		<para>
		MI FIFO Command usage:
		</para>
		<programlisting  format="linespecific">
opensipsctl fifo cc_list_queue
</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>
		<function moreinfo="none">cc_list_flows</function>
		</title>
		<para>
		Command to list all the flows - for each flow, the 
		following attributes will be printed: the flow ID, the avg. call 
		duration, how many calls were processed, how many agents are logged, 
		and how many onging calls are.
		</para>
		<para>
		It takes no parameter.
		</para>
		<para>
		MI FIFO Command usage:
		</para>
		<programlisting  format="linespecific">
opensipsctl fifo cc_list_flows
</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>
		<function moreinfo="none">cc_list_agents</function>
		</title>
		<para>
		Command to list all the agents - for each agent, the 
		following attributes will be printed: agent ID, agent login state and
		agent state (free, wrapup, incall).
		</para>
		<para>
		It takes no parameter.
		</para>
		<para>
		MI FIFO Command usage:
		</para>
		<programlisting  format="linespecific">
opensipsctl fifo cc_list_agents
</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>
		<function moreinfo="none">cc_list_calls</function>
		</title>
		<para>
		Command to list all the ongoing calls - for each call, the 
		following attributes will be printed: call ID, call state 
		(welcome, queued, toagent, ended), call duration, flow it belongs to,
		agent serving the call (if any).
		</para>
		<para>
		It takes no parameter.
		</para>
		<para>
		MI FIFO Command usage:
		</para>
		<programlisting  format="linespecific">
opensipsctl fifo cc_list_agents
</programlisting>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>
		<function moreinfo="none">cc_reset_stats</function>
		</title>
		<para>
		Command to reset all counter-like statistics.
		</para>
		<para>
		It takes no parameter.
		</para>
		<para>
		MI FIFO Command usage:
		</para>
		<programlisting  format="linespecific">
opensipsctl fifo cc_reset_stats
</programlisting>
	</section>

	</section>


	<section>
	<title>Exported pseudo-variables</title>
	<para>
	NONE
	</para>
	</section>



</chapter>

